import { Question } from 'exampro-shared';

export const POLITICAL_LAW_QUESTIONS: Question[] = [
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 1,
        "Question": "Seamacho, an overseas seafarer who still had two years remaining on his contract when he was illegally terminated, and who would only be entitled to a maximum of six-month’s pay under the reinstated provision, engages you as his counsel. How are you to argue that the new law is invalid insofar as it brings back to the statute books a provision that has already been struck down by the Court? .",
        "Answer": "I will argue that since Section 10 of Republic Act No. 8042 has already been declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court, its nullity cannot be cured by reincorporation or reenactment of the same or a similar law or provision. Once a law has been declared unconstitutional, it remains unconstitutional unless circumstances have so changed as to warrant a reverse conclusion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 2,
        "Question": "Congressman Sugar Oil authored a bill called House Bill No, 0056 which legalizes jueteng. When the Bill became law (RA 10156), Fr. Nosu Gal, a priest, filed a petition seeking for the nullification of RA 10156 on th ground that it is unconstitutional as it violates Section 13, Article II, of the 1987 Constitution which states that 'The state recognizes the vital role of the youth in nation-building and shall promote and protect their physical, moral, spiritual, intellectual, and social well-being'. Fr. Gal filed the petition as a concerned citizen and as taxpayer. Does Fr. Gal have locus standi?",
        "Answer": "No, because Fr. Gal has no personal and substantial interest that will be prejudiced by the implementation of the law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 3,
        "Question": "In an amendment to the constitution by 'initiative and referendum', the 'initiative' phase is meant that the people propose the amendments. There is a valid proposal when a proposition has received the approval of:",
        "Answer": "at least 3% of the registered voters of each province and 12% of the total number of registered voters nationwide."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 4,
        "Question": "With the passage of time, the members of the House of Representatives increased with the creation of new legislative districts and the corresponding adjustments in the number of party-list representatives. At a time when the House membership was already 290, a great number of the members decided that it was time to propose amendments to the Constitution. The Senators, however, were cool to the idea. But the members of the House insisted. They accordingly convened Congress into a constituent assembly in spite of the opposition of the majority of the members of the Senate. When the votes were counted, 275 members of the House of Representatives approved the proposed amendments. Only 10 Senators supported such proposals. The proponents now claim that the proposals were validly made, since more than the required three-fourths vote of Congress has been obtained. The 14 Senators who voted against the proposals claim that the proposals needed not three-fourths vote of the entire Congress but each house. Since the required number of votes in the Senate was not obtained, then there could be no valid proposals, so argued the Senators. Were the proposals validly adopted by Congress? ",
        "Answer": "The proposal were not validly adopted, because the ten (10) Senators who voted in favor of the proposed amendments constituted less than three-fourths of all the Members of the Senate. Although Section 1, Article XVII of the Constitution did not expressly provide that the Senate and the House of Representatives must vote separately, when the Legislature consist of two (2) houses, the determination of one house is to be submitted to the separate determination of the other house."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 5,
        "Question": "A priority thrust of the Administration is the change of the form of government from unitary to federal. The change can be effected only through constitutional amendment or revision. (a) What are the methods of amending the Constitution? Explain briefly each method. ",
        "Answer": "The Constitution may be amended or revised by the vote of at least three fourths of all the Members of Congress, acting as a Constituent Assembly, by way of a proposal. Any amendment or revision under this provision shall be valid upon ratification by a majority of the votes cast in a plebiscite which shall be held not earlier than 60 days or later than 90 days after the approval of the amendment or revision. The Constitution may also be amended or revised by a Constitutional Convention. Congress may, by the vote of at least two-thirds of all its members, call a Constitutional Convention, or by a majority vote of all its Members subject to the electorate the calling of a Constitutional Convention. Any amendment or revision under this provision shall be valid in the same manner as in Article XVII, Sec. 1(1) of the 1987 Constitution. Amendments to the Constitution may be directly proposed by the people through initiative upon petition of at least 12% of the registered voters, and at least 3% of the registered voters in every legislative district must be represented. The people cannot propose revisions and may propose only amendments. The petition must be signed by the required number of people, and the full text of the proposed amendments must be embodied in the petition. Any amendment under Article XVII, Sec. 2 of the 1987 Constitution, shall be valid when ratified by a majority of the votes cast in a plebiscite which shall be held not earlier than sixty days nor later than ninety days after the certification by the Commission on Elections of the sufficiency of the petition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 6,
        "Question": "Jose Cruz and 20 others filed a petition with the COMELEC to hold a plebiscite on their petition for initiative to amend the Constitution by shifting to a unicameral parliamentary form of government. Assuming that the petition has been signed by the required number of registered voters, will it prosper?",
        "Answer": "No, since they seek, not an amendment, but a revision."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 7,
        "Question": "Cite at least three provisions of the Constitution that need to be amended or revised to effect the change from unitary to federal, and briefly explain why? ",
        "Answer": "Examples of provisions that need to be amended or revised to effect the change from unitary to federal: 1. Article X, Sec. 3 must be omitted because the legislature will no longer define the scope of the powers of the government. 2. Article X, Sec. 4 will have to be omitted. The President will no longer have the power of supervision over local governments. 3. Article X, Sec. 5 must be omitted. Congress will no longer be allowed to impose limitations on the power of taxation of local governments."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 8,
        "Question": "All public officers and employees shall take an oath to uphold and defend the Constitution.",
        "Answer": "The statement is true. This is expressly provided for in Section 4, Article IX-B of the 1987 Constitution."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 9,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is a non-self-executing provision of the Constitution:",
        "Answer": "the state shall encourage and support researches and studies on the arts and culture."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 10,
        "Question": "(1) A bill was introduced in the House of Representatives in order to implement faithfully the provisions of the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS) to which the Philippines is a signatory. Congressman Pat Rio Tek questioned the constitutionality of the bill on the ground that the provisions of UNCLOS are violative of the provisions of the Constitution defining the Philippine internal waters and territorial sea. Do you agree or not with the said objection? Explain.  (2) Describe the following maritime regimes under UNCLOS  (a) Territorial sea (b) Contiguous zone (c) Exclusive economic zone (d) Continental shelf",
        "Answer": "(1) I do not agree. 'The UNCLOS is a product of international negotiation that seeks to balance State sovereignity (mare clausum) and the principle of freedom of the high seas (mare liberum). The freedom to use the world’s marine waters is one of the oldest customary principles of international law. The UNCLOS gives to the coastal State sovereign rights in varying degrees over the different zones of the sea which are: 1) internal waters, 2) territorial sea, 3) contiguous zone, 4) exclusive economic zone, and 5) the high seas. It also gives coastal States more or less jurisdiction over foreign vessels depending on where the vessel is located. Insofar as the internal waters and territorial sea is concerned, the Coastal State exercises sovereignty, subject to the UNCLOS and other rules of international law. Such sovereignty extends to the air space over the territorial sea as well as to its bed and subsoil.' UNCLOS III does not define the internal and territorial waters of states but merely 'prescribes the water-land ration, length and contour of baselines of archipelagic States like the Philippines.' 'UNCLOS III has nothing to do with the acquisition (or loss) of territory,' It is a multilateral treaty regulating, among others, sea-use rights over maritime zones (i.e., the territorial waters [12 nautical miles from the baselines], exclusive economic zone [200 nautical miles from the baselines]), and continental shelves that UNCLOS III delimits.' 'UNCLOS III and its ancillary baselines laws play no role in the acquisition, enlargement or, as petitioners claim, diminution of territory. Under traditional international law typology, States acquire (or conversely, lose) territory through occupation, accretion, cession and prescription, not by executing multilateral treaties on the regulations of sea-use rights or enacting statutes to comply with the treaty’s terms to delimit maritime zones and continental shelves. Territorial claims to land features are outside UNCLOS III, and are instead governed by the rules on general international law.' (2) Under the provisions of UNCLOS III- (a) The territorial waters of an archipelagic state shall extend up to 12 nautical miles from its baselines; (b) Its contiguous zone shall extend up to 24 nautical miles from its baselines; (c) Its exclusive economic zone shall extend up to 200 nautical miles from its baselines; while (d) Its continental shelf 'comprises the seabed and subsoil of the submarine areas that extend beyond its territorial sea throughout the natural prolongation of its land territory to the outer edge of the continental margin, or to a distance of 200 nautical miles from the baselines from which the breadth of the territorial sea is measured where the outer edge of the continental margin does not extend up to that distance.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 11,
        "Question": "Congress passed Republic Act No. 7711 to comply with the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. In a petition filed with the Supreme Court, Anak Ti Ilocos, an association of Ilocano professionals, argued that Republic Act No. 7711 discarded the definition of the Philippine territory under the Treaty of Paris and in related treaties; excluded the Kalayaan Islands and the Scarborough Shoals from the Philippine Archipelagic baselines; and converted internal waters into archipelagic waters. Is the petition meritorious? (6%)",
        "Answer": "No, the petition is not meritorious. The United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea has nothing to do with the acquisition or loss of territory. It merely regulates sea-use rights over maritime zones, contiguous zones, exclusive economic zones, and continental shelves which it delimits. The Kalayaan Islands and the Scarborough Shoals are located at an appreciable distance from the nearest shoreline of the Philippines archipelago. A straight baseline loped around them from the nearest baseline will violate Article 47(3) and Article 47(2) of the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea III. Whether the bodies of water lying landward of the baselines of the Philippines are internal waters or archipelagic waters, the Philippines retains jurisdiction over them."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 12,
        "Question": "Under the archipelago doctrine, the waters around, between, and connecting the islands of the archipelago form part of the territorial sea of the archipelagic state.",
        "Answer": "False. Under Article I of the Constitution, the water around, between and connecting the islands of the Philippines form part of its internal waters. Under Article 49 (1) of the U.N. Convention on the Law of the Sea, these waters do not form part of the territorial sea but are described as archipelagic waters."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 13,
        "Question": "(A) Define the archipelagic doctrine of national territory, state its rationale; and explain how it is implemented through the straight baseline method.  (B) Section 2 of RA 9522 declared the Kalayaan Island Group (KIG) and Scarborough Shoal as 'Regimes of Islands.' Professor Agaton contends that since the law did not enclose said islands, then the Philippines lost its sovereignty and jurisdiction over them. Is his contention correct? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "(A) By the term 'archipelagic doctrine of national territory' is meant that the islands and waters of the Philippine archipelago are unified in sovereignty, together with 'all the territories over which the Philippines has sovereignty or jurisdiction.' This archipelagic doctrine, so described under Article I of the Constitution, draws its rationale from the status of the whole archipelago in sovereignty by which under Part IV of the UNCLOS, the Philippines is defined as an Archipelagic State in Article 46, thus: a) archipelagic state means a State constituted wholly by one or more archipelagos and may include other islands; b) archipelago means a group of islands including parts of islands interconnecting Waters and other natural features which are so closely interrelated that such islands waters and other natural features form an intrinsic geographic, economic and political entity, or which historically have been regarded as such. As an archipelagic state, the national territory is implemented by drawing its 'straight archipelagic baselines.' pursuant to Article 47 of the UNCLOS which prescribes among its main elements, as follows: 1. By 'joining the outermost points of the outermost islands and drying reefs of the archipelago', including the main islands and an area in which the ratio of the area of the water to the land, including atolls, is between 1 to land 9 to 1. 2 Mainly, the length of such baselines 'shall not exceed 100 nautical lines...' 3 The drawing of such baselines shall not depart to any appreciable extent from the general configuration of the archipelago.' (B) The contention Prof. Agaton is not correct at all. 'Regime of islands is a concept provided in Article 121 of the UNCLOS. It is a definition of the island as 'a naturally formed area a land, surrounded by water which is above water at high tide.' On the other hand, this provision, is differentiated from 'rocks' which cannot sustain human habitation of their own. - The importance of the difference between a natural island and rock is that an island is provided with territorial sea, exclusive economic zone and continental shelf, whereas rocks have no exclusive economic zone and continental shelf. This is the difference by which RA 9522 introduced into the KIG and separately Panatag or Scarborough Shoal is an island. 'Regime of Islands', has no relevance to acquisition or loss of sovereignty. RA 9522 has the effect of possibly dividing the area in question into island and rocks, apparently to make clear for each the maritime zones involved in the definition of island or of rocks."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 14,
        "Question": "The Ambassador of the Republic of Kafirista referred to you for handling, the case of the Embassy’s Maintenance Agreement with CBM, a private domestic company engaged in maintenance work. The Agreement binds CBM, for a defined fee, to maintain the Embassy’s elevators, air-conditioning units and electrical facilities. Section 10 of the Agreement provides that the Agreement shall be governed by Philippine laws and that any legal action shall be brought before the proper court of Makati. Kafiristan terminated the Agreement because CBM allegedly did not comply with their agreed maintenance standards. CBM contested the termination and filed a complaint against Kafiristan before the Regional Trial Court of Makati. The Ambassador wants you to file a motion to dismiss on the ground of state immunity from suit and to oppose the position that under Section 10 of the Agreement, Kafiristan expressly waives its immunity from suit. Under these facts, can the Embassy successfully invoke immunity from suit? (6%)",
        "Answer": "Yes, the Embassy can invoke immunity from suit. Section 10 of the Maintenance Agreement is not necessarily a waiver of sovereign immunity from suit. It was meant to apply in case the Republic of Kafiristan elects to sue in the local courts or waives its immunity by a subsequent act. The establishment of a diplomatic mission is a sovereign function. This encompasses its maintenance and upkeep. The Maintenance Agreement was in pursuit of a sovereign activity."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 15,
        "Question": "In the last quarter of 2012, about 5,000 container vans of imported goods intended for the Christmas Season were seized by agents of the Bureau of Customs. The imported goods were released only on January 10, 2013. A group of importers got together and filed an action for damages before the Regional Trial Court of Manila against the Department of Finance and Bureau of Customs. The Bureau of Customs raised the defense of immunity from suit and, alternatively, that liability should lie with XYZ Corp. which the Bureau had contracted for the lease of ten (10) high powered van cranes but delivered only five (5) of these cranes, thus causing the delay in its cargo-handling operations. It appears that the Bureau, despite demand, did not pay XYZ Corp. the Php1.0 Million deposit and advance rental required under their contract. (A) Will the action by the group of importers prosper? ",
        "Answer": "No. The action by the group of importers will not prosper. The primary function of the Bureau of Customs is governmental, that of assessing and collecting lawful revenues from imported articles and all other tariff and customs duties, fees, charges, fines and penalties."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 16,
        "Question": "Mr. Sinco Sued the government for damages. After trial, the court ruled in his favor and awarded damages amounting to P50 million against the government. To satisfy the judgment against the government, which valid option is available to Mr. Sinco? ",
        "Answer": "File a claim with the Commission on Audit (COA) pursuant to Commonwealth Act 327, as amended by Presidential Decree 1445."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 17,
        "Question": "The LISS Liberty, a warship of the United States (U.S.), entered Philippine archipelagic waters on its way to Australia. Because of the negligence of the naval officials on board, the vessel ran aground off the island of Palawan, damaging coral reefs and other marine resources in the area. Officials of Palawan filed a suit for damages against the naval officials for their negligence, and against the U.S., based on Articles 30 and 31 of the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS). Article 31 provides that the Flag State shall bear international responsibility for any loss or damage to the Coastal State resulting from noncompliance by a warship with the laws and regulations of the coastal State concerning passage through the territorial sea. The U.S. Government raised the defenses that: (A) The Philippine courts cannot exercise jurisdiction over another sovereign State, including its warship and naval officials.  (B) The United States is not a signatory to UNCLOS and thus cannot be bound by its provisions.  Rule on the validity of the defenses raised by the U.S., with reasons.",
        "Answer": "The defenses raised by the U.S. Government are not valid. (A) This defense relies on sovereign immunity from suit as advanced by the U.S. Government. But the suit filed by the Officials of Palawan draws its strength from Article 30 and 31 of the UN Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS). However, the U.S. defense is defeated by the UNCLOS through the application of Article 32 which provides: 'With such exceptions as are contained in sub-section A and in Articles 30 and 37, nothing in this Convention affects the immunities of warships and other government ships operated for non-commercial purposes.' In reality the supreme relevance of Article 32 quoted above is actualized by quoting an existing U.S. government document sourced from Dispatch Supplement, Law of the Sea Convention: Letters of Transmittal and Submittal and Commentary, as follows: 'Article 32 provides, in effect that the only rules in the Convention derogating from the immunities of warships and government ships operated for non-government purposes are those found in Articles 17-26, 30 and 31.' (B) The U.S. Government turns to the defense that it is not bound by the UNCLOS for the reason that it is not a State Party or a signatory. However, to be bound by the principle, it does not have to be a party to a treaty or convention. If it has the normative status of a customary norm of international law, it is binding on all states. This appears to be the holding of the principle of immunity of warship in question, as upheld by the U.S. Government in the document cited above. It states from the UNCLOS, thus: 'The Convention protects and strengthens the key principle of sovereign immunity for war-ships...Although not a new concept, sovereign immunity is a principle or of vital importance to the United States. The Convention provides for a universally recognized formulation of this principle... Article 32 provides that, with such exceptions as are contained in subsection A and in Articles 30 and 31… nothing in the Convention affects the immunities of warships...'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 18,
        "Question": "Under the doctrine of immunity from suit, the State cannot be sued without its consent. How may the consent be given by the State? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The State may be sued, with its consent, either expressly or impliedly. Only Congress can give a written waiver of immunity from suit in the form of a law. If a government agency undertakes a proprietary function, It waives its Immunity from suit When the Philippines Tourism Authority entered into a contract for the construction of a golf course, it engaged in a proprietary function."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 19,
        "Question": "The doctrine of immunity from suit in favor of the State extends to public officials in the performance of their official duties. May such officials be sued nonetheless to prevent or to undo their oppressive or illegal acts, or to compel them to act? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Public officials may be sued if they acted oppressively or illegally in the performance of their duties. A suit against a public officer who acted illegally is not a suit against the state. A public official may be compelled to act through a writ of mandamus. The main objective of mandamus is to compel the performance of a ministerial duty on the part of the respondent official; however, the writ does not issue to control or review the exercise of discretion or to compel a course of conduct. The writ of prohibition can also be availed of, as it is an extraordinary writ which can be directed against a public officer ordering said officer to desist from further proceedings when said proceedings are without or in excess of said officer’s jurisdiction, or are accompanied with grave abuse of discretion. Lastly, a public officer is by law not immune from damages in his/her personal capacity for acts done in bad faith which, being outside the scope of his authority, are no longer protected by the mantle of immunity for official actions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 20,
        "Question": "Do government-owned or -controlled corporations also enjoy the immunity of the State from suit? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "A government-owned or controlled corporation may be sued. A suit against it is not a suit against the State, because it has a separate juridical personality."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 21,
        "Question": "A law that makes military service for women merely voluntary is constitutional.",
        "Answer": "False. In the defense of the state, all citizens may be required by law to render personal, military or civil service. The duty is imposed on all citizens without distinction as to gender."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 22,
        "Question": "Angelina, a married woman, is a Division Chief in the Department of Science and Technology. She had been living with a married man, not her husband, for the last fifteen (15) years. Administratively charged with immorality and conduct prejudicial to the best interest of the service, she admits her live-in arrangement, but maintains that this conjugal understanding is in conformity with their religious beliefs. As members of the religious sect, Yahweh’s Observers, they had executed a Declaration of Pledging Faithfulness which has been confirmed and blessed by their Council of Elders. At the formal investigation of the administrative case, the Grand Elder of the sect affirmed Angelina’s testimony and attested to the sincerity of Angelina and her partner in the profession of their faith. If you were to judge this case, will you exonerate Angelina? Reasons. ",
        "Answer": "Angelina should be exonerated. First, it has not been shown that there is compelling state interest which will be undermined by granting her an exemption. Second, it has not been shown that the least intrusive means possible was used so that the free exercise of religion is not infringed any more than necessary."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 23,
        "Question": "Meanwhile, Jenny, also a member of Yahweh’s Observers, was severely disappointed at the manner the Grand Elder validated what she considered was an obviously immoral conjugal arrangement between Angelina and her partner. Jenny filed suit in court, seeking the removal of the Grand Elder from the religious sect on the ground that his act in supporting Angelina not only ruined the reputation of their religion, but also violated the constitutional policy upholding the sanctity of marriage and the solidarity of the family. Will Jenny’s case prosper? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The case will not prosper. This involves the performance of the official functions of religious authorities. Because of separation of Church and State, courts must respect the autonomy of the religious sect in such matters."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 24,
        "Question": "The Philippine Government is negotiating a new security treaty with the United States which could involve engagement in joint military operations of the two countries’ armed forces. A loose organization of Filipinos, the Kabataan at Matatandang Makabansa (KMM) wrote the Department of Foreign Affairs (DFA) and the Department of National Defense (DND) demanding disclosure of the details of the negotiations, as well as copies of the minutes of the meetings. The DFA and the DND refused, contending that premature disclosure of the offers and counter- offers between the parties could jeopardize on-going negotiations with another country. KMM filed suit to compel disclosure of the negotiation details, and be granted access to the records of the meetings, invoking the constitutional right of the people to information on matters of public concern. Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The petition of KMM must be denied. Diplomatic negotiations are privileged in order to encourage a frank exchange of exploratory ideas between the parties by shielding the negotiations from public view."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 25,
        "Question": "Will your answer be the same if the information sought by KMM pertains to contracts entered into by the Government in its proprietary or commercial capacity? Why or why not? ",
        "Answer": "KMM is entitled to have access to information pertaining to government contracts entered into by the Government in the exercise of its proprietary or commercial capacity. The right to information under the Constitution does not exclude contracts of public interest and are not privileged."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 26,
        "Question": "Several concerned residents of the areas fronting Manila Bay, among them a group of students who are minors, filed a suit against the Metro Manila Development Authority (MMDA), the Department of Environment and Natural Resources (DENR), the Department of Health (DOH), the Department of Agriculture (DA), the Department of Education (DepEd), the Department of Interior and Local Government (DILG), and a number of other executive agencies, asking the court to order them to perform their duties relating to the cleanup, rehabilitation and protection of Manila Bay. The complaint alleges that the continued neglect by defendants and their failure to prevent and abate pollution in Manila Bay constitute a violation of the petitioners constitutional right to life, health and a balanced ecology. (B) In its decision which attained finality, the Court ordered the defendants to clean up, rehabilitate and sanitize Manila Bay within eighteen (18) months, and to submit to the Court periodic reports of their accomplishment, so that the Court can monitor and oversee the activities undertaken by the agencies in compliance with the Court's directives. Subsequently a resolution was issued extending the time periods within which the agencies should comply with the directives covered by the final decision. A view was raised that the Court’s continued intervention after the cases has been decided violates the doctrine separation of powers considering that the government agencies all belong to the Executive Department and are under the control of the President. Is this contention correct? Why or why not? .",
        "Answer": "The order of the Supreme Court to the defendants to clean up, rehabilitate and sanitize Manila Bay is an exercise of judicial power, because the execution of its decision is an integral part of its adjudicative function. Since the submission of periodic reports is needed to fully implement the decision, the Supreme Court can issue a continuing writ of mandamus to the Metropolitan Manila Development Authority until full compliance with its order is shown."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 27,
        "Question": "Congress passed a bill appropriating P100-billion. Part of the money is to be used for the purchase of a 200-hectare property in Antipolo. The rest shall be spent for the development of the area and the construction of the Universal Temple for all the World's Faiths (UTAW-P). When completed, the site will be open, free of charge, to all religions, beliefs, and faiths, where each devotee or believer shall be accommodated and treated in a fair and equal manner, without distinction, favor, or prejudice. There will also be individual segments or zones in the area which can be used for the conduct of whatever rituals, services, sacraments, or ceremonials that may be required by the customs or practices of each particular religion. The President approved the bill, happy in the thought that this could start the healing process of our wounded country and encourage people of varied and often conflicting faiths to live together in harmony and in peace. The law is questioned in the ground that it violates Sec. 5, Article II of the Constitution that 'no law shall be made respecting an establishment of religion or prohibiting the free exercise thereof,' how will you resolve the challenge? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "The contention must be rejected. The use of the site temple will not be limited to a particular religious sect. It will be made available to all religious sects. The temporary use of public property for religious purposes without discrimination does not violate the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 28,
        "Question": "Which phrase best completes the statement - The starting point of the principle of separation of powers is the assumption of the division of the functions of government into three distinct classes:",
        "Answer": "the executive, the legislative, and the judicial."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 29,
        "Question": "Senator Fleur De Lis is charged with plunder before the Sandiganbayan. After finding the existence of probable cause, the court issues a warrant for the Senator's arrest. The prosecution files a motion to suspend the Senator relying on Section 5 of the Plunder Law. According to the prosecution, the suspension should last until the termination of the case. Senator Lis vigorously opposes the motion contending that only the Senate can discipline its members; and that to allow his suspension by the Court would violate the principle of separation of powers. Is Senator Lis's contention tenable? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "The Senators contention in untenable or 'unavailing.' He can be validly preventively suspended under the Plunder Law. The power of each House of Congress to 'punish its Members for disorderly behavior,' and 'suspend or expel a Member' by a vote of two-thirds of all its Members subject to the qualification that the penalty of suspension, when imposed, should not exceed sixty days' under Section 6 (3). Article VI of the Constitution is 'distinct' from the suspension under the Plunder Law, 'which is not a penalty but a preliminary, preventive measure, prescinding from the fact that the latter is not being imposed on petitioner for misbehavior as a Member of the House of Representatives.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 30,
        "Question": "The 'Poverty Alleviation and Hunger Mitigation Act' was passed by Congress to address the twin problems of poverty and hunger. The Act created the Poverty Alleviation and Hunger Mitigation Commission (PAHMC), composed of the Secretary of Social Welfare and Development, as Chairman, and the Secretaries of Agriculture, Agrarian Reform, and Education, as members. The Commission is authorized to formulate and implement programs to address poverty and hunger, and to allocate funds for the purpose. The Act also provides that the Commission shall have the power to issue summons, subpoena, and subpoena duces tecum, and to punish direct contempt. The constitutionality of the Act is challenged on the ground that it violates the doctrine of separation of powers. Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The Act is unconstitutional. The power to punish contempt is inherent in judicial power. It may not be conferred by law to an administrative body."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 31,
        "Question": "The Department of Agrarian Reform (DAR) issued Administrative Order (AO) No. 06-08, which provides that 'all agrarian law implementers (ALIs) shall undergo a mandatory training program on agrarian reform and social justice to be conducted by the DAR Academy.' The DAR Academy is a government-owned and -controlled corporation (GOCC) created by law to provide training and education on agrarian reform. The AO also provides that 'no ALI shall be promoted to a higher position unless he/she has completed the mandatory training program.' The League of Provincial Agrarian Reform Officers (LOPARO) filed a petition for prohibition with the Supreme Court, seeking to nullify AO No. 06-08 on the ground that it violates the principle of separation of powers. LOPARO argues that the power to prescribe qualifications for public office is legislative in nature, and cannot be delegated to an administrative agency. Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The petition must be dismissed. The power of the DAR to issue the AO is valid. The power to prescribe qualifications for public office is not exclusively legislative. The Civil Service Commission, as the central personnel agency of the government, is empowered to prescribe all qualifications for any position in the civil service. The DAR, as an administrative agency, may be validly authorized by law to issue rules and regulations to carry out its mandate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 32,
        "Question": "The President issued an executive order creating the Presidential Commission on Good Government (PCGG) and gave it the power to investigate and prosecute cases involving the ill-gotten wealth of the former President, his family, and cronies. The PCGG filed a case against Mr. X for the recovery of ill-gotten wealth. Mr. X moved to dismiss the case on the ground that the PCGG has no power to prosecute because the power to prosecute is exclusively vested in the Office of the Ombudsman. Is the motion tenable? ",
        "Answer": "The motion is not tenable. The power of the PCGG to prosecute cases involving the recovery of ill-gotten wealth is valid. The power to prosecute is executive in nature and is vested in the President. The President may delegate this power to the PCGG. The power of the Ombudsman to investigate and prosecute is not exclusive. It is shared with other agencies of government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 33,
        "Question": "Section 8 of P.D. No. 910, entitled 'Creating an Energy Development Board, defining its. powers and functions, Providing funds therefor and for other purposes,' provides that: 'All fees, revenues and receipts of the Board from any and all sources x x x shall form part of a Special Fund to be used to finance energy resource development and exploitation programs and projects of the government and for such other purposes as may be hereafter directed by the President.' The Malampaya NGO contends that, the provision constitutes an undue delegation of legislative power since the phrase 'and for such other purposes as may be hereafter directed by the President gives the President unbridled discretion to determine the purpose for which the funds will be used. On the other hand, the government urges the application of ejusdem generis. (A) Explain the 'completeness test' and 'sufficient standard test.'  (B) Does the assailed portion of section 8 of PD 910 hurdle the two (2) tests? ",
        "Answer": "(A) The completeness test means that the law sets forth the policy to be executed, carried out or implemented by the delegate. The 'sufficient standard test' means the law lays down adequate guidelines or limitations to map out the boundaries of the authority of the delegate and prevent the delegate from running riot. The standard must specify the limits of the authority of the delegate, announce the legislative policy and identify the condition under which it is to be implemented. (B) The assailed portion of Presidential Decree No. 910 does not satisfy the two tests. The phrase and for such other purposes as may be hereafter directed by the President' gives the President unbridled discretion to determine the purpose for which the funds will be used. An infrastructure is any basic facility needed by society. The power to determine what kind of infrastructure to prioritize and fund is a power to determine the purpose of the appropriation and is an undue delegation of the power to appropriate. The assailed provision does not fall under the principle of ejusdem generis. First, the phrase 'energy resource development and exploitation programs and projects. of the government states a singular and general class. Second, it exhausts the class it represents."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 34,
        "Question": "The Constitution declares that the Philippines is a republican state. Republicanism means:",
        "Answer": "the representatives of the government are elected by the people."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 35,
        "Question": "Identify which one is an invalid exercise of the legislative power:",
        "Answer": "law authorizing the President, in times of war or other national emergency, for a limited period, subject to prescribed restrictions, to exercise powers necessary and proper to carry out a declared national policy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be changed by an ordinary law enacted by Congress?",
        "Answer": "Commencement of the term of office of Senators."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 37,
        "Question": "Congress shall have the sole power to declare the existence of a state of war by vote of - ",
        "Answer": "two-thirds of both Houses in joint session, voting separately."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 38,
        "Question": "Under the enrolled bill doctrine, the signing of a bill by both the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the Senate and the certification by the secretaries of both Houses of Congress that the bill was passed on a certain date are conclusive on the bill's due enactment. Assuming there is a conflict between the enrolled bill and the legislative journal, to the effect that the enrolled bill signed by the Senate President and eventually approved by the President turned out to be different from what the Senate actually passed as reflected in the legislative journal. (a) May the Senate President disregard the enrolled bill doctrine and consider his signature as invalid and of no effect? ",
        "Answer": "(a) The Senate President may withdraw his signature from the bill since it was not actually the bill that was approved by Congress, so there was no enrolled bill to speak of."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 39,
        "Question": "Under the enrolled bill doctrine, the signing of a bill by both the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the Senate and the certification by the secretaries of both Houses of Congress that the bill was passed on a certain date are conclusive on the bill's due enactment. Assuming there is a conflict between the enrolled bill and the legislative journal, to the effect that the enrolled bill signed by the Senate President and eventually approved by the President turned out to be different from what the Senate actually passed as reflected in the legislative journal. (b) May the President thereafter withdraw his signature? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "(b) Yes, he can because of the prior withdrawal of the signature of Senate President and Speaker; accordingly, there could be no 'enrolled bill' that could have been validly approved."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 40,
        "Question": "Sec. 26(2), Art. VI of the Constitution provides that no bill passed by either House of Congress shall become a law unless it has passed three readings on separate days and printed copies of it in its final form have been distributed to the Members of the House three days before its passage. Is there an exception to the provision? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The exception to this provision is when the President certifies to the necessity of its immediate enactment to meet a public calamity or necessity."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 41,
        "Question": "Several citizens, unhappy with the proliferation of families dominating the political landscape, decided to take matters into their own hands. They proposed to come up with a people’s initiative defining political dynasties. They started a signature campaign for the purpose of coming up with a petition for that purpose. Some others expressed misgivings about a people’s initiative for the purpose of proposing amendments to the Constitution, however. They cited the Court’s decision in Santiago v. Commission on Elections, 270 SCRA 106 (1997), as authority for their position that there is yet no enabling law for such purpose. On the other hand, there are also those who claim that the individual votes of the justices in Lambino v. Commission on Elections, 505 SCRA 160 (2006), mean that Santiago’s pronouncement has effectively been abandoned. If you were consulted by those behind the new attempt at a people’s initiative, how would you advise them? ",
        "Answer": "I shall advise those starting a people’s initiative that initiative to pass a law defining political dynasties may proceed as their proposal is to enact a law only and not to amend the constitution. The decision in Santiago v. Commission on Elections, 270 SCRA 106 [1997], which has not been reversed, upheld the adequacy of the provisions in Republic Act 6735 on initiative to enact a law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 42,
        "Question": "What are the essential elements of a valid petition for a people's initiative to amend the 1987 Constitution? Discuss. ",
        "Answer": "The elements of a valid petition for a people's initiative are the following: 1. At least twelve per cent (12%) of the registered voters, of which every legislative district must be represented by at least three per cent  of the registered voters in it, should directly sign the entire proposal; and 2. The draft of the proposed amendment must be embodied in the petition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 43,
        "Question": "A law making 'Bayan Ko' the new national anthem of the Philippines, in lieu of 'Lupang Hinirang,' is constitutional.",
        "Answer": "True. Congress may by law adopt a new national anthem, but it shall take effect only upon ratification by the people in a national referendum."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 44,
        "Question": "A candidate for Senator must be at least 35 years old on",
        "Answer": "the day he files his certificate of candidacy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 45,
        "Question": "A few months before the end of the present Congress, Strongwill was invited by the Senate to shed light in an inquiry relative to the alleged siphoning and diverting of the pork barrel of members of Congress to non-existent or fictitious projects. Strongwill has been identified in the news as the principal actor responsible for the scandal, the leader of a non-governmental organization which ostensibly funnelled the funds to certain local government projects which existed only on paper. At the start of the hearings before the Senate, Strongwill refused at once to cooperate. The Senate cited him in contempt and sent him to jail until he would have seen the light. The Congress, thereafter, adjourned sine die preparatory to the assumption to office of the newly-elected members. In the meantime, Strongwill languished behind bars and the remaining senators refused to have him released, claiming that the Senate is a continuing body and, therefore, he can be detained indefinitely. Are the senators right? ",
        "Answer": "The Senators are right. The Senate is to be considered as a continuing body of purposes of its exercise of its power punish for contempt. Accordingly, the continuing validity of its orders punishing for contempt should not be affected by its sine die adjournment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 46,
        "Question": "The rule in Article V1, Section 5 (3) of the Constitution that 'Each legislative district shall comprise, as far as practicable, contiguous, compact and adjacent territory' is a prohibition against:",
        "Answer": "gerrymandering."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 47,
        "Question": "Article V1, Section 5(3) of the Constitution requires that for a city to be entitled to have at least one representative, its population shall be at least:",
        "Answer": "250,000."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 48,
        "Question": "Gerrymandering refers to the practice of: ",
        "Answer": "creating or dividing congressional districts in a manner intended to favor a particular party or candidate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 49,
        "Question": "Greenpeas is an ideology-based political party fighting for environmental causes. It decided to participate under the party-list system. When the election results came in, it only obtained 1.99 percent of the votes cast under the party-list system. Bluebean, a political observer, claimed that Greenpeas is not entitled to any seat since it failed to obtain at least 2% of the votes. Moreover, since it does not represent any of the marginalized and underrepresented sectors of society, Greenpeas is not entitled to participate under the party-list system. How valid are the observations of Bluebean? ",
        "Answer": "The claim of Bluebean that Greenpeas is not entitled to a seal under the party-list-system because it obtained only 1.99 percent of the votes cast under the party-list-system is not correct. Since the provision in Section 5 (2). Article VI of the Constitution that the party-list representatives shall constitute twenty percent (20%) of the total number of the members of the House of Representatives is mandatory, after the parties receiving at least two percent  of the total votes case for the party-list system have been allocated one seat, the remaining seats should be allocated among the parties by the proportional percentage of the votes received by each party as against the total party-list votes. The claim of Bluebean that Greenpeas is not entitled to participate in the party-list elections because it does not represent any marginalized and underrepresented sectors of society is not correct. It is enough that its principal advocacy pertains to the special interest of its sector."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 50,
        "Question": "The Partido ng Mapagkakatiwalaang Pilipino (PMP) is a major political party which has participated in every election since the enactment of the 1987 Constitution. It has fielded candidates mostly for legislative district elections. In fact, a number of its members were elected, and are actually serving, in the House of Representatives. In the coming 2016 elections, the PMP leadership intends to join the party-list system. Can PMP join the party-list system without violating the Constitution and Republic Act (R.A.) No. 7941? ",
        "Answer": "Yes. As for political parties, they may participate in the party-list race by registering under the party-list system and no longer field congressional candidates. These parties, if they field congressional candidates, however, are not barred from participating in the party-list elections; what they need to do is register their sectoral wing or party under the party-list system. This sectoral wing shall be considered an 'independent sectoral party' linked to a political party through a coalition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 51,
        "Question": "Rudy Domingo, 38 years old, natural-born Filipino and a resident of the Philippines since birth, is a Manila-based entrepreneur who runs KABAKA, a coalition of peoples’ organizations from fisherfolk communities. KABAKA’s operations consist of empowering fisherfolk leaders through livelihood projects and trainings on good governance. The Dutch Foundation for Global Initiatives, a private organization registered in The Netherlands, receives a huge subsidy from the Dutch Foreign Ministry, which, in turn is allocated worldwide to the Foundation’s partners like KABAKA. Rudy seeks to register KABAKA as a party-list with himself as a nominee of the coalition. Will KABAKA and Rudy be qualified as a party-list and a nominee, respectively? Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "KABAKA and Ruby are not qualified as a party list and as nominee, respectively, since KABAKA is receiving a subsidy from the Dutch Foreign Ministry. Under Section 2(5), Article IX-C of the Constitution, a political party which is supported by any foreign government cannot be registered with the Commission on Elections."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 52,
        "Question": "A Senator or Member of the House of Representatives shall be privileged from arrest while Congress is in session for all offenses punishable by imprisonment of not more than:",
        "Answer": "six years imprisonment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 53,
        "Question": "No Senator or member of the House of Representatives may personally appear as counsel before:",
        "Answer": "any court of justice."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 54,
        "Question": "In the May 2013 elections, the Allied Workers’ Group of the Philippines (AWGP), representing land-based and sea-based workers in the Philippines and overseas, won in the party list congressional elections. Atty. Abling, a labor lawyer, is its nominee. As part of the party’s advocacy and services, Congressman Abling engages in labor counseling, particularly for local workers with claims against their employers and for those who need representation in collective bargaining negotiations with employers. When labor cases arise, AWGP enters its appearance in representation of the workers and the Congressman makes it a point to be there to accompany the workers, although a retained counsel also formally enters his appearance and is invariably there. Congressman Abling largely takes a passive role in the proceedings although he occasionally speaks to supplement the retained counsel’s statements. It is otherwise in CBA negotiations where he actively participates. Management lawyers, feeling aggrieved that a congressman should not actively participate before labor tribunals and before employers because of the influence a congressman can wield, filed a disbarment case against the Congressman before the Supreme Court for his violation of the Code of Professional Responsibility and for breach of trust, in relation particularly with the prohibitions on legislators under the Constitution. Is the cited ground for disbarment meritorious? (6%)",
        "Answer": "Being a congressman, Atty. Abling is disqualified under Article VI, Section 14 of the 1987 Constitution from personally appearing as counsel before quasi-judicial and other administrative bodies handling labor cases constitutes personal appearance before them. His involvement in collective bargaining, negotiations also involves practice of law, because he is making use of his legal knowledge for the benefit of others. The Bureau of Labor Relations is involved in collective bargaining negotiations. Atty. Abling should not be disbarred but should be merely suspended from the practice of law. Suspension is the appropriate penalty for involvement in the unlawful practice of law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 55,
        "Question": "Senator Bondoc was charged with murder and detained at the Quezon City Jail. He invoked, in seeking leave from the court to attend the session of the Senate, his immunity from arrest as a Senator. How should the court rule on his motion?",
        "Answer": "Deny the motion since immunity from arrest does not apply to a charge of murder."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 56,
        "Question": "Congresswoman A is a co-owner of an industrial estate in Sta. Rosa, Laguna which she had declared in her Statement of Assets and Liabilities. A member of her political party authored a bill which would provide a 5-yeal development plan for all industrial estates in the Southern Tagalog Region to attract investors. The plan included an appropriation of 2 billion pesos for construction of roads around the estates. When the bill finally became law, a civil society watchdog questioned the constitutionality of the law as it obviously benefitted Congresswoman A's industrial estate. Decide' with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The law is constitutional. Section 12, Article VI of the Constitution does not prohibit the enactment of a law which will benefit the business interests of a member of the Senate or the House of Representatives. It only requires that if the member of Congress whose business interests will be benefited by the law is the one who will file the bill, he should notify the House concerned of the potential conflict of interest."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 57,
        "Question": "When an elective official's preventive suspension will result in depriving his constituents of his services or representation, the court may",
        "Answer": "shorten the period of such suspension."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 58,
        "Question": "Sec. 17, Art. VI of the Constitution establishes an Electoral Tribunal for each of the Houses of Congress, and makes each Electoral Tribunal 'the sole judge of all contests relating to the election, returns, and qualifications of their respective Members.' On the other hand, Sec. 2(1), C (Commission on Elections), Alt IX of the Constitution grants to the COMELEC the power to enforce and administer all laws and regulations 'relative to the conduct of an election, plebiscite, initiative, referendum, and recall?' Considering that there is no concurrence of jurisdiction between the Electoral Tribunals and the COMELEC, state when the jurisdiction of the Electoral Tribunals begins, and the COMELEC's jurisdiction ends. Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "To be considered a Member of the House of Representatives, there must be a concurrence of the following requisites: (1) a valid proclamation, (2) a proper oath, and (3) assumption of office. Once a winning candidate has been proclaimed and taken his oath, and assumed office as a Member of the House of Representatives, the jurisdiction of the Commission on Elections over the election contest ends, and the jurisdiction of the House of Representatives Electoral Tribunal begins."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 59,
        "Question": "During a period of national emergency. Congress may grant emergency powers to the President. State the conditions under which such a venture is allowed.",
        "Answer": "Under Section 23(2), Article VI of the Constitution, Congress may grant the President emergency powers subject to the following conditions: 1. There is a war or other national emergency; 2. The grant of emergency powers must be for a limited period; 3. The grant of emergency powers is subject to such restrictions as Congress may prescribe; and 4. The emergency powers must be exercised to carry out a declared national policy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 60,
        "Question": "True or False. A proclamation of a state of emergency is sufficient to allow the President to take over any public utility. (0.5%)",
        "Answer": "The statement that a proclamation of emergency is .sufficient to allow the President to take over any public utility is false. Since it is an aspect of emergency powers, in accordance with Section 23(2), Article VI of the Constitution, there must be a law delegating such power to the President."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 61,
        "Question": "The President issued Proclamation 9517 declaring a state of emergency and calling the armed forces to immediately carry out necessary measures to suppress terrorism and lawless violence. In the same proclamation, he directed the government’s temporary takeover of the operations of all privately owned communication utilities, prescribing reasonable terms for the takeover. Is the takeover valid?",
        "Answer": "No, it is a power reserved for Congress alone."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 62,
        "Question": "A statutory provision requiring the President or an administrative agency to present the proposed implementing rules and regulations of a law to Congress which by itself or through a committee formed by it, retains a 'right' or 'power' to approve or disapprove such regulations before they may take effect, is a:",
        "Answer": "legislative veto."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 63,
        "Question": "The President issued an executive order directing all department heads to secure his consent before agreeing to appear during question hour before Congress on matters pertaining to their departments. Is the executive order unconstitutional for suppressing information of public concern?",
        "Answer": "No, the President has the power to withhold consent to appearance by his department heads during question hour."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 64,
        "Question": "Congressman Nonoy delivered a privilege speech charging the Intercontinental Universal Bank (IUB) with the sale of unregistered foreign securities, in violation of R.A. 8799. He then filed, and the House of Representatives unanimously approved, a Resolution directing the House Committee on Good Government (HCGG) to conduct an inquiry on the matter, in aid of legislation, in order to prevent the recurrence of any similar fraudulent activity. The HCGG immediately scheduled a hearing and invited the responsible officials of IUB, the Chairman and Commissioners of the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), and the Governor of the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas (BSP). On the date set for the hearing, only the SEC Commissioners appeared, prompting Congressman Nonoy to move for the issuance of the appropriate subpoena ad testificandum to compel the attendance of the invited resource persons. The IUB officials filed suit to prohibit HCGG from proceeding with the inquiry and to quash the subpoena, raising the following arguments: a. The subject of the legislative investigation is also the subject of criminal and civil actions pending before the courts and the prosecutor’s office; thus, the legislative inquiry would preempt judicial action; ",
        "Answer": "The argument is not tenable; since this is an essential component of legislative power, it cannot be made subordinate to criminal and civil actions. Otherwise, it would be very easy to subvert any investigation in aid of legislation through the convenient ploy of instituting criminal and civil actions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 65,
        "Question": "Congressman Nonoy delivered a privilege speech charging the Intercontinental Universal Bank (IUB) with the sale of unregistered foreign securities, in violation of R.A. 8799. He then filed, and the House of Representatives unanimously approved, a Resolution directing the House Committee on Good Government (HCGG) to conduct an inquiry on the matter, in aid of legislation, in order to prevent the recurrence of any similar fraudulent activity. The HCGG immediately scheduled a hearing and invited the responsible officials of IUB, the Chairman and Commissioners of the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), and the Governor of the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas (BSP). On the date set for the hearing, only the SEC Commissioners appeared, prompting Congressman Nonoy to move for the issuance of the appropriate subpoena ad testificandum to compel the attendance of the invited resource persons. The IUB officials filed suit to prohibit HCGG from proceeding with the inquiry and to quash the subpoena, raising the following arguments: b. Compelling the IUB officials, who are also respondents in the criminal and civil cases in court, to testify at the inquiry would violate their constitutional right against self-incrimination.  Are the foregoing arguments tenable? Reasons.",
        "Answer": "The argument is untenable. Since the IUB officials were not being subjected to a criminal penalty, they cannot invoke their right against self-incrimination unless a question calling for an incriminating answer is propounded."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 66,
        "Question": "Congressman Nonoy delivered a privilege speech charging the Intercontinental Universal Bank (IUB) with the sale of unregistered foreign securities, in violation of R.A. 8799. He then filed, and the House of Representatives unanimously approved, a Resolution directing the House Committee on Good Government (HCGG) to conduct an inquiry on the matter, in aid of legislation, in order to prevent the recurrence of any similar fraudulent activity. The HCGG immediately scheduled a hearing and invited the responsible officials of IUB, the Chairman and Commissioners of the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), and the Governor of the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas (BSP). On the date set for the hearing, only the SEC Commissioners appeared, prompting Congressman Nonoy to move for the issuance of the appropriate subpoena ad testificandum to compel the attendance of the invited resource persons. The IUB officials filed suit to prohibit HCGG from proceeding with the inquiry and to quash the subpoena, raising the following arguments: c. May the Governor of the BSP validly invoke executive privilege and, thus, refuse to attend the legislative inquiry? Why or why not? ",
        "Answer": "No, because the power to invoke executive privilege is limited to the President."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 67,
        "Question": "In the exercise of its power of legislative inquiries and oversight functions, the House of Representatives or the Senate may only ask questions",
        "Answer": "that are relevant to the proposed legislation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 68,
        "Question": "Provisions unrelated to an appropriation bill are considered prohibited. These are called:",
        "Answer": "riders."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 69,
        "Question": "The requirement that 'Every bill shall embrace only one subject which shall be expressed in the title thereof' prevents:",
        "Answer": "log-rolling legislation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 70,
        "Question": "If by the end of any fiscal year, the Congress shall have failed to pass the general appropriations bill for the ensuring fiscal year, the general appropriations law for the preceding fiscal year shall be deemed:",
        "Answer": "re-enacted."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 71,
        "Question": "Senator GSC proposed a bill increasing excise taxes on tobacco and alcohol products. The generated incremental revenues shall be used for the universal health care program for all Filipinos and for tobacco farmers’ livelihood. After the Senate passed the bill on third reading, it was transmitted to the House of Representatives which approved the bill in toto. The President eventually signed it into law. Atty. JFC filed a petition before the Supreme Court, questioning the constitutionality of the new law. Is the law constitutional? ",
        "Answer": "None of the above is correct."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 72,
        "Question": "A treaty which provides tax exemption needs no concurrence by a majority of all the Members of the Congress. (0.5%)",
        "Answer": "The statement that a treaty which provides tax exemption needs no concurrence by a majority of all the Members of Congress is true. It is only a law, not a treaty, granting a tax exemption which requires the concurrence of a majority of all the Members of Congress. Without respect to its lawful substantive content, a treaty, to be valid and effective, requires concurrence by at least two-thirds of all the Members of the Senate."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 73,
        "Question": "Congress passed a bill appropriating P50 million in assistance to locally based television stations subject to the condition that the amount would be available only in places where commercial national television stations do not operate. The President approved the appropriation but vetoed the condition. Was the veto valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, since the vetoed condition may be separated from the item."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 74,
        "Question": "Give the limitations on the power of the Congress to enact the General Appropriations Act? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Sections 24 and 25 of Article VI provide the limitations on the power of Congress to enact General Appropriations Acts. All appropriation, revenue or tariff bills, bills authorizing increase of the public debt, bills of local application, and private bills shall originate exclusively in the House of Representatives, but the Senate may propose or concur with amendments. The Congress may not increase the appropriations recommended by the President for the operation of the Government as specified in the budget. The form, content, and manner of preparation of the budget shall be prescribed by law. No provision or enactment shall be embraced in the general appropriations bill unless it relates specifically to some particular appropriation therein. Any such provision or enactment shall be limited in its operation to the appropriation to which it relates. The procedure in approving appropriations for the Congress shall strictly follow the procedure for approving appropriations for other departments and agencies. A special appropriations bill shall specify the purpose for which it is intended, and shall be supported by funds actually available as certified by the National Treasurer, or to be raised by a corresponding revenue proposed therein. No law shall be passed authorizing any transfer of appropriations; however, the President, the President of the Senate, the Speaker of the House of Representatives, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, and the heads of Constitutional Commissions may, by law, be authorized to augment any item in the general appropriations law for their respective offices from savings in other items of their respective appropriations. Discretionary funds appropriated for particular officials shall. be disbursed only for public purposes to be supported .by appropriate vouchers and subject to such guidelines as may be prescribed by law. If, by the end of any fiscal year, the Congress shall have failed to pass the general appropriations bill for the ensuing fiscal year, the general appropriations law for the preceding fiscal year shall be deemed reenacted and shall remain in force and effect until the general appropriations bill is passed by the Congress."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 75,
        "Question": "May an incumbent Justice of the Supreme Court be disbarred as a lawyer?",
        "Answer": "Yes, by the Supreme Court itself."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 76,
        "Question": "Sec. 3, Art. XI of the Constitution states that [n]o impeachment proceedings shall be initiated against the same official more than once within a period of one year.' What constitutes initiation of impeachment proceedings under the provision? ",
        "Answer": "Initiation of impeachment proceedings under Article XI, Sec. 3 of the Constitution starts with the filing of the complaint. The initiation of impeachment proceedings starts with the filing of the complaint, and the vote of one-third of the House in a resolution of impeachment does not initiate the impeachment proceedings which was already initiated by the filing of a verified complaint under Section 3, paragraph (2), Article XI of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 77,
        "Question": "The Chief Justice appointed X, the President's sister, as Assistant Court Administrator in the Supreme Court during the President's tenure. Claiming that the Constitution prohibits the appointment in government of a President's relative, a taxpayer asks for its nullification. Will the challenge prosper?",
        "Answer": "No, the position to which X was appointed is not among those prohibited under the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 78,
        "Question": "When the President contracted a personal loan during his incumbency, he may be sued for sum of money",
        "Answer": "after his term of office."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 79,
        "Question": "Upon complaint of the incumbent President of the Republic, 'A' was charged with libel before the Regional Trial Court. 'A' moved to dismiss the information on the ground that the Court had no jurisdiction over the offense charged because the President, being immune from suit, should also be disqualified from filing a case against 'A' in court. Resolve the motion.",
        "Answer": "The motion should be denied according to Soliven vs. Makasiar, 167 SCRA 393, the immunity of the President from suit is personal to the President. It may be invoked by the President only and not by any other person."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 80,
        "Question": "During his incumbency, President Carlos shot to death one of his advisers during a heated argument over a game of golf that they were playing. The deceased adviser’s family filed a case of homicide against President Carlos before the city prosecutor's office. He moved to dismiss the case, invoking presidential immunity from suit. Should the case be dismissed?",
        "Answer": "No, his immunity does not cover crimes involving moral turpitude."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 81,
        "Question": "Distinguish 'presidential communications privilege' from 'deliberative process privilege.' .",
        "Answer": "Presidential communications privilege applies to decision-making of the President. The deliberative process privilege applies to decision-making of executive officials. Unlike the 'deliberative process privilege,' 'the presidential communications privilege' applies to documents in their entirety and covers final and post decisional matters, as well as pre-deliberative ones. The deliberative process privilege includes advisory opinions, recommendations and deliberations comprising part of a process by which governmental decisions and policies are formulated."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct? ",
        "Answer": "Congress may, by law, provide limitations on the President's power to contract or guarantee foreign loans on behalf of the Republic of the Philippines."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 83,
        "Question": "The President appointed Dexter I. Ty as Chairperson of the COMELEC on June 14, 2011 for a term of seven (7) years pursuant to the 1987 Constitution. His term of office started on June 2, 2011 to end on June 2, 2018. Subsequently, the President appointed Ms. Marikit as the third member of the COMELEC for a term of seven (7) years starting June 2, 2014 until June 2, 2021. On June 2, 2015, Chairperson Ty retired optionally after having served the government for thirty (30) years. The President then appointed Commissioner Marikit as COMELEC Chairperson. The Commission on Appointments confirmed her appointment. The appointment papers expressly indicate that Marikit will serve as COMELEC Chairperson 'until the expiration of the original term of her office as COMELEC Commissioner or on June 2, 2021.' Matalino, a tax payer, files a petition for certiorari before the Supreme Court asserting that the appointment of Marikit as COMELEC Chairperson is unconstitutional for the following reasons: (1) The appointment of Marikit as COMELEC Chairperson constituted a reappointment which is proscribed by Section 1 (2), Article IX of the 1987 Constitution; and (2) the term of office expressly stated in the appointment papers of Marikit likewise contravenes the aforementioned constitutional provision. Will the constitutional challenge succeed? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The first argument is untenable since Commissioner Marikit was not reappointed but actually was a promotional appointment as she had not yet fully served her term. What the Constitution prohibits is a reappointment of a COMELEC Commissioner after serving the seven-year term. On the second argument, the limitation of the term of Commissioner Marikit as chairman until expiration of her original term on June 2, 2021 is valid only until June 8, 2018, that is, the unexpired portion of the last chairman’s term but invalid if until 2021 as it exceeds the limitation. A promotional apportionment is allowed provided that the aggregate period of the term of the appointee will not exceed seven years and that the rotational scheme of staggering terms of the commission membership is maintained."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 84,
        "Question": "While Congress was in session, the President appointed eight acting Secretaries. A group of Senators from the minority bloc questioned the validity of the appointments in a petition before the Supreme Court on the ground that while Congress is in session, no appointment that requires confirmation by the Commission on Appointments can be made without the latter’s consent and that an undersecretary should instead be designated as Acting Secretary. Should the petition be granted? ",
        "Answer": "No, the petition should not be granted. The Department Head is an alter ego of the president and must enjoy his confidence even if the appointment will be merely temporary. The Senators cannot require the President to designate an Undersecretary to be the temporary alter ego of the president."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 85,
        "Question": "Since the Constitution is silent as to who can appoint the Chairman of the Commission on Human Rights, the President appointed W to that position without submitting his appointment to the Commission on Appointments for confirmation. Is W’s appointment by the President valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, since the power to appoint in the government, if not lodged elsewhere, belongs to the President as Chief Executive."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 86,
        "Question": "An appointment held at the pleasure of the appointing power",
        "Answer": "essentially temporary in nature."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 87,
        "Question": "A was a career Ambassador when he accepted an ad interim appointment as cabinet Member. The Commission on Appointment bypassed his ad interim appointment, however, and he was not re-appointed. Can he re-assume his position as career Ambassador? ",
        "Answer": "The career Ambassador cannot re-assume his position as career Ambassador. His ad interim appointment as Cabinet Member was a permanent appointment. He abandoned his position as Ambassador when he accepted his appointment as Cabinet Member because as Cabinet Member, he could not hold any other office during his tenure."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 88,
        "Question": "The President’s appointment of an acting secretary although Congress is in session is",
        "Answer": "valid."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 89,
        "Question": "The President appoints the Vice President as his Administration’s Housing Czar, a position that requires the appointee to sit in the Cabinet. Although the appointment of the members of the Cabinet requires confirmation by the Commission on Appointment (CA), the Office of the President does not submit the appointment to the CA. May the Vice President validly sit in the Cabinet? ",
        "Answer": "The Vice President may validly sit in the Cabinet even if he was not confirmed by the Commission on Appointments. Under Article VII, Sec. 3 of the Constitution, the appointment of the Vice President as cabinet member requires no confirmation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 90,
        "Question": "Whose appointment is NOT subject to confirmation by the Commission on Appointments?",
        "Answer": "Executive Secretary"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 91,
        "Question": "Margie has been in the judiciary for a long time, starting from the lowest court. Twenty (20) years from her first year in the judiciary, she was nominated as a Justice in the Court of Appeals. Margie also happens to be a first-degree cousin of the President. The Judicial and Bar Council included her in the short-list submitted to the President whose term of office was about to end - it was a month before the next presidential elections. Can the President still make appointments to the judiciary during the so-called midnight appointment ban period? Assuming that he can still make appointments, could he appoint Margie, his cousin? ",
        "Answer": "The President can make appointments to the Supreme Court two months before a presidential election until the end of his term but not to the rest of the Judiciary like the Court of Appeals. Under Section 4(1), Article VIII of the Constitution, vacancies in the Supreme Court shall be filled within ninety (90) days from the occurrence of the vacancy. Under Section 9, Article VIII of the Constitution, vacancies in the lower courts shall be filled within ninety (90) days from submission of the list of nominees. These appointments to the courts, which is what is sought to be prevented by the prohibition. The President may also appoint his first cousin, Margie, as Justice of the Court of Appeals. The prohibition in Section 13, Article VII of the Constitution against appointment by the president of relatives within the fourth degree by consanguinity or affinity does not include appointments to the judiciary."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 92,
        "Question": "The independent economic planning agency of the Government as provided for by the Constitution is the:",
        "Answer": "National Economic Development Authority."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 93,
        "Question": "Who has control of the expenditure of public funds? ",
        "Answer": "The Office of the President through the Department of Budget and Management."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 94,
        "Question": "The Independent Central Monetary Authority of the Government is the:",
        "Answer": "Central Bank of the Philippines."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 95,
        "Question": "When the President orders the Chief of the Philippine National Police to suspend the issuance of permits to carry firearms outside the residence, the President exercises",
        "Answer": "the power of control."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 96,
        "Question": "The President exercises the power of control over all executive departments and agencies, including government-owned or controlled corporations.",
        "Answer": "True. Under Section 18, Article VII of the Constitution the President has control of all executive departments, bureaus and offices. His power of control extends to agencies with respect to their administrative functions, even if they are performing quasi-judicial functions and to government-owned or controlled corporations."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 97,
        "Question": "Under the so-called doctrine of qualified political agency, ",
        "Answer": "the acts of subordinates presumptively of those of the heads of offices disapproves them."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 98,
        "Question": "A law provides that the Secretaries of the Departments of Finance and Trade and Industry, the Governor of the Central Bank, the Director General of the National Economic Development Authority, and the Chairperson of the Philippine Overseas Construction Board shall sit as ex-officio members of the Board of Directors (BOD) of a government owned and controlled corporation (GOCC). The other four (4) members shall come from the private sector. The BOD issues a resolution to implement a new organizational structure, staffing pattern, a position classification system, and a new set of qualification standards. After the implementation of the Resolution, Atty. Dipasupil questioned the legality of the Resolution alleging that the BOD has no authority to do so. The BOD claims otherwise arguing that the doctrine of qualified political agency applies to the case. It contends that since its agency is attached to the Department of Finance, whose head, the Secretary of Finance, is an alter ego of the President, the BOD’s acts were also the acts of the President. Is the invocation of the doctrine by the BOD proper? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The invocation by the Board of directors of the doctrine of qualified political agency is not proper. 'The doctrine of qualified political agency essentially postulates that the heads of the various executive departments are the alter egos of the President, and, thus, the actions taken by such heads in the performance of their official duties are deemed the acts of the President unless the President himself should disapprove such acts. This doctrine is in recognition of the fact that in our presidential form of government, all executive organizations are adjuncts of a single Chief executive; that the heads of the executive Departments are assistants and agents of the Chief Executive; and that the multiple executive functions of the president as the Chief Executive are performed through the Executive Departments. The doctrine has been adopted here out of practical necessity, considering that the President cannot be expected to personally perform the multifarious functions of the executive office. The Cabinet Members sat on the Board of Directors ex officio, or by reason of their office or function, 'not because of their direct appointment to the Board by the president. Evidently, it was the law, not the President, that sat them in the Board.' 'Under the circumstances, when the members of the Board of Directors effected the assailed… reorganization, that were acting as the responsible members of the Board of Directors' constituted pursuant to the law,' not as the alter egos of the President.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 99,
        "Question": "Jax Liner applied for a public utility bus service from Bacolod to Dumaguete from the Land Transportation Franchising and Regulatory Board (LTFRB). BB Express opposed. LTFRB ruled in favor of Jax. BB appealed to the Secretary of the Department of Transportation and Communication (DOTC), who reversed the LTFRB decision. Jax appealed to the Office of the President which reinstated the LTFRB’s ruling. BB Express went to the Court of Appeals on certiorari questioning the decision of the Office of the President on the ground that Office of the President has no jurisdiction over the case in the absence of any law providing an appeal from DOTC to the Office of the President. Will the petition prosper?",
        "Answer": "No, the action of the DOTC Secretary bears only the implied approval of the President who is not precluded from reviewing the decision of the former."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 100,
        "Question": "Distinguish the President’s authority to declare a state of rebellion from the authority to proclaim a state of national emergency. ",
        "Answer": "While both the power to declare a state of rebellion and the power to proclaim a state of national emergency may be justified under the President’s general Ordinance Powers under the provisions of the Administrative Code (Chapter 2, Book III of Executive Order No. 292 Administrative Code of 1987), the power to declare a state of rebellion springs from the President’s so called 'calling out power' under Section 18 of Article VII of the Constitution, which provides that 'whenever it becomes necessary, he may call out such armed forces to prevent or suppress lawless violence, invasion or rebellion,' while the power to proclaim a state of national emergency can be said to be based primarily on his duty to enforce the laws as well as to formulate policies to be embodied in existing laws, consistent with the provisions of Section 17 of Article VII of the Constitution. Under said provision, the President 'sees to it that all laws are enforced by the officials and employees of his department.' Moreover, 'in the exercise of such function, the President, if needed, may employ the powers attached to this office as the Commander-in-Chief of all armed forces of the country, including the Philippine National Police under the Department of Interior and Local Government.' It must be noted though, that without a law promulgated pursuant to the provisions of Section 23(2) of Article VI, and Section 17 of Article XII, both of which authorize the statutory delegation of emergency powers in favor of the President, he is limited to the exercise of his calling-out power under Section 18 of Article VII of the Constitution, and may not exercise emergency powers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 101,
        "Question": "The President CANNOT call out the military",
        "Answer": "to enforce customs laws."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 102,
        "Question": "The President may proclaim martial law over a particular province subject to revocation or extension",
        "Answer": "by Congress alone."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 103,
        "Question": "The President cannot grant pardon in cases of impeachment. He may however exercise such power when:",
        "Answer": "A person convicted in an impeachment proceeding is subject to prosecution, trial and punishment in an ordinary criminal action."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 104,
        "Question": "Following COMELEC Chairman Bocay’s conviction for acts of corruption in the impeachment proceedings, he was indicted for plunder before the Sandiganbayan and found guilty, as charged. Can he get Presidential pardon on the plunder case?",
        "Answer": "Yes, conviction in court in a criminal action is subject to the President’s pardoning power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 105,
        "Question": "What is the pardoning power of the President under Art VIII, Sec. 19 of the Constitution? Is the exercise of the power absolute? ",
        "Answer": "Except in cases of impeachment, or as otherwise provided in this Constitution, the President may grant reprieves, commutations and pardons, and remit fines and forfeitures, after conviction by final judgment. He shall also have the power to grant amnesty with the concurrence of a majority of all the Members of the Congress. No pardon, amnesty, parole, or suspension of sentence for violation of election laws, rules, and regulations shall be granted by the President without the favorable recommendation of the Commission. The only instances in which the President may not extend pardon remain to be in: (1) impeachment cases; (2) cases that have not yet resulted in a final conviction; and (3) cases involving violations of election laws, rules and regulations in which there was no favorable recommendation coming from the COMELEC. Any act Of Congress by way of statute cannot operate to delimit the pardoning power of the President."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 106,
        "Question": "Distinguish pardon from amnesty. ",
        "Answer": "1. Pardon can be given only after final conviction; amnesty can be given any time and even before the Ming of a criminal case. 2. Pardon looks forward; amnesty looks backward, as if the accused never committed a crime. 3. Pardon is given to individuals. Amnesty is given to a class of persons. 4. Pardon is given for all criminal offenses. Amnesty is given for political offenses. 5. Pardon does not require the concurrence of Congress. Amnesty requires the concurrence of Congress. 6. Pardon must be proven, because it is a private act; amnesty need not be proven, because it is a public act."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 107,
        "Question": "The President entered into an executive agreement with Vietnam for the supply to the Philippines of animal feeds not to exceed 40,000 tons in any one year. The Association of Animal Feed Sellers of the Philippines questioned the executive agreement for being contrary to R.A. 462 which prohibits the importation of animal feeds from Asian countries. Is the challenge correct? ",
        "Answer": "Yes, the executive agreement is contrary to an existing domestic law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 108,
        "Question": "The Philippines and the Republic of Kroi Sha established diplomatic relations and immediately their respective Presidents signed the following: (1) Executive Agreement allowing the Republic of Kroi Sha to establish its embassy and consular offices within Metro Manila; and (2) Executive Agreement allowing the Republic of Kroi Sha to bring to the Philippines its military complement, warships, and armaments from time to time for a period not exceeding one month for the purpose of training exercises with the Philippine military forces and exempting from Philippine criminal jurisdiction acts committed in the line of duty by foreign military personnel, and from paying custom duties on all the goods brought by said foreign forces into Philippine territory in connection with the holding of the activities authorized under the said Executive Agreement. Senator Maagap questioned the constitutionality of the said Executive Agreements and demanded that the Executive Agreements be submitted to the Senate for ratification pursuant to the Philippine Constitution. Is Senator Maagap correct? Explain. ( 4 % )",
        "Answer": "It is submitted that only the first Executive Agreement regarding the establishment of the embassy of Kroi Sha need not be submitted to the Senate for its concurrence following the general rule that the Executive Agreements need not to submitted to the Senate for its concurrence, under the provisions of Section 21 of Article VII of the Constitution. The second Executive Agreement which allows the Republic of Kroi Sha to bring to the Philippines its military complement, warships, and armaments from time may be subject to the provisions of Section 25 of Article XVIII of the Constitution, which provides that 'foreign bases, troops or facilities shall not be allowed in the Philippines except under a treaty duly concurred in by the Senate and, when the Congress so requires, ratified by a majority of the votes cast by the people in a national referendum held for that purpose, and recognized as a treaty by the of the contracting state.' It should be noted that, under the Constitution, the Senate merely provides its concurrence to, and does not ratify, treaties. It is the President who ratifies treaties."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 109,
        "Question": "The President forged an executive agreement with Vietnam for a year supply of animal feeds to the Philippines not to exceed 40,000 tons. The Association of Animal Feed Sellers of the Philippines questioned the executive agreement for being contrary to R.A. 462 which prohibits the importation of animal feeds from Asian countries. Is the challenge correct?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the executive agreement is contrary to our existing domestic law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 110,
        "Question": "The League of Filipino Political Scientists (LFPS) organized an international conference on the human rights situation in Myanmar at the Central Luzon State University (CLSU). An exiled Myanmar professor Sung Kui, critical of the military government in Myanmar, was invited as keynote speaker. The Secretary. of Foreign Affairs informed the President of the regional and national security implications of having Prof. Kui address the conference. The President thereupon instructed the immigration authorities to prevent the entry of Prof. Kui into Philippine territory. The chancellor of CLSU argued that the instruction violates the Constitution. Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The argument of the chancellor of Central Luzon State University is not valid. Since an alien has no right to enter the Philippines, preventing Prof. Sing Kui from entering the Philippines is not a violation of his rights. Since the President has the power of control over. foreign relations, be has the power to ban aliens from entering the Philippines."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 111,
        "Question": "The Philippines entered into an international agreement with members of the international community creating the International Economic Organization (1E0) which will serve as a forum to address economic issues between States, create standards, encourage greater volume of trade between its members, and settle economic disputes. After the Philippine President signed the agreement, the Philippine Senate demanded that the international agreement be submitted to it for its ratification. The President refused, arguing that it is an executive agreement that merely created an international organization and it dwells mainly on addressing economic issues among States. Is the international agreement creating the 1E0 a treaty or an executive agreement? Explain, ",
        "Answer": "The agreement creating the International Economic Organization (1E0) is an executive agreement and not a treaty. In Section 21, Article VII is the only provision of the Constitution which defines a 'treaty or international agreement' as valid and effective law by reason of concurrence of the Senate. However, it is the amendment of the Constitution that such 'treaty or international agreement' does not include executive agreement which therefore is excluded from the Senate's authority of concurrence over treaties. This constitutional intent is expressed in the proceedings of the Constitutional Commission in its awareness that at the time the power of the President to conclude executive agreement was clearly recognized by at least decisions of the Supreme court establishing the principle that the President’s power includes conclusion of executive agreements which are valid without need of Senate concurrence, Hence, logically the Treaty Clause in Section 21, Article VII is to be interpreted as excluding executive agreement. Moreover, as the Supreme Court has pointed out in Pimentel v. Office of the Executive Secretary, the President has the sole power to ratify treaties. The Senate may be able to exercise its authority of concurrence only if the President transmits the instrument of ratification by which he accepts the terms agreed on by his diplomatic negotiators of the proposed treaty in question, together with the text of the proposed treaty, with the request addressed to the Senate President to ratify such proposed treaty as requested by the President. It is only on the basis of the authority of the President to ratify treaties that the Senate may act in concurrence under the Treaty clause of the Constitution."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 112,
        "Question": "The President may contract or guarantee foreign loans on behalf of the Republic of the Philippines only upon prior concurrence of the:",
        "Answer": "Monetary Board."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 113,
        "Question": "The President, concerned about persistent reports of widespread irregularities and shenanigans related to the alleged ghost projects with which the pork barrel funds of members of Congress had been associated, decided not to release the funds authorized under a Special Appropriations Act for the construction of a new bridge. The Chief Executive explained that, to properly conserve and preserve the limited funds of the government, as well as to avoid further mistrust by the people, such a project - which he considered as unnecessary since there was an old bridge near the proposed bridge which was still functional - should be scrapped. Does the President have such authority? ",
        "Answer": "The Presidential has the authority to withhold the release of the funds under a Special Appropriation Act for a Project which he considered unnecessary. The faithful execution of the laws requires the President to desist from implementing a law if by doing so will prejudice public interest. It is folly to require the President to spend the entire amounts appropriated in the law in such a case."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 114,
        "Question": "The Executive Department has accumulated substantial savings from its appropriations. Needing P3,000,000.00 for the conduct of a plebiscite for the creation of a new city but has no funds appropriated soon by the Congress for the purpose, the COMELEC requests the President to transfer funds from the savings of the Executive Department in order to avoid a delay in the holding of the plebiscite. May the President validly exercise his power under the 1987 Constitution to transfer funds from the savings of the Executive Department, and make a cross-border transfer of P3,000,000.00 to the COMELEC by way of augmentation? Is your answer the same if the transfer is treated as aid to the COMELEC? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The President may not transfer savings to the Commission on Elections as aid. The constitutional prohibition against the transfer of appropriations to other branches of government or Constitutional Commission applies for whatever reason."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 115,
        "Question": "The President may set a limit on the country’s import quota in the exercise of his",
        "Answer": "delegated power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 116,
        "Question": "The power of the President to veto any particular part in an appropriation revenue, or tariff bill, is called the:",
        "Answer": "item veto."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 117,
        "Question": "Distinguish between 'pocket veto' and 'item veto.' ",
        "Answer": "A pocket veto is when the President is considered to have rejected a bill submitted to him for his approval when Congress adjourns during the period given to the President to approve or reject a bill. On the other hand, an item veto, or partial veto, is the power of a President to nullify or cancel specific provisions of a bill, usually a budget appropriations bill, without vetoing the entire legislative package."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 118,
        "Question": "Several senior officers of the Armed Forces of the Philippines received invitations from the Chairperson of the Senate Committees on National Defense and Security for them to appear as resource persons in scheduled public hearings regarding a wide range of subjects. The invitations state that these public hearings were triggered by the privilege speeches of the Senators that there was massive electoral fraud during the last national elections. The invitees Brigadier General Matapang and Lieutenant Coronel Makatuwiran, who were among those tasked to maintain peace and order during the last election, refused to attend because of an Executive Order banning all public officials enumerated in paragraph 3 thereof from appearing before either house of Congress without prior approval of the President to ensure adherence to the rule of executive privilege. Among those included in the enumeration are 'senior officials of executive departments who, in the judgment of the department heads, are covered by executive privilege.' Several individuals and groups challenge the constitutionality of the subject executive order because it frustrates the power of the Congress to conduct inquiries in aid of legislation under Section 21, Article VI of the 1987 Constitution. Decide the case. ",
        "Answer": "Under Section 5, Article XVI of the Constitution, the President is the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces of the Philippines. By virtue of this power, the President can prevent the Brigadier General Matapang and Lieutenant Colonel Makatwiran from appearing before the Senate to testify before a legislative investigation. The provision in the Executive Order which authorized Department Secretaries to invoke executive privilege in case senior officials in their departments are asked to appear in a legislative investigation is unconstitutional. It is upon the President that executive power is vested. Only the President can make use of Executive Privilege."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 119,
        "Question": "The House Committee on Appropriations conducted an inquiry in aid of legislation into alleged irregular and anomalous disbursements of the Countrywide Development Fund (CDF) and Congressional Initiative Allocation (CIA) of Congressmen as exposed by X, a Division Chief of the Department of Budget and Management (DBM). Implicated in the questionable disbursement are high officials of the Palace. The House Committee summoned X and the DBM Secretary to appear and testify. X refused to appear, while the Secretary appeared but refused to testify invoking executive privilege. May X be compelled to appear and testify? If yes, what sanction may be imposed on him? ",
        "Answer": "X may be compelled to appear and testify. Only the President or the Executive Secretary by order of the President can invoke executive privilege. He can be cited for contempt and ordered to be arrested."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 120,
        "Question": "A department secretary may, with the President’s consent, initiate his appearance before the Senate or the House of Representatives which",
        "Answer": "must accept such initiated appearance."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 121,
        "Question": "Is the Budget Secretary shielded by executive privilege from responding to the inquiries of the House Committee? Explain briefly. If the answer is no, is there any sanction that may be imposed upon him? ",
        "Answer": "The Secretary of Budget and Management is not shielded by executive privilege from responding to the inquiries of the House Committee on Appropriations, because the inquiry is aid of legislation and neither the President nor the Executive Secretary by order of the President invoked executive privilege. For refusing to testify, he may cited for contempt and ordered to be arrested."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 122,
        "Question": "What is the concept of expanded judicial review under the 1987 Constitution?",
        "Answer": "The concept of expanded judicial review of the Supreme Court, the facial challenge to the constitutionality laws is no longer limited to laws which violate the freedom of speech but applies to all violations of fundamental rights under the Bill of Rights. In addition, the remedies of certiorari and prohibition in the Supreme Court are broader in scope and may be issued to correct errors of jurisdiction of judicial, quasi-judicial, or ministerial actions and may be invoked to restrain any act of grave abuse of discretion of any branch of government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 123,
        "Question": "Differentiate the rule-making power or the power of the Supreme Court to promulgate rules under Section 5, Article VIII of the 1987 Constitution and judicial legislation. ",
        "Answer": "Judicial legislation refers to the encroachment by the Judiciary upon the function of the legislature by making law rather than declaring, construing or enforcing the law. Section 3 (5), Article VIII of Constitution granted the Supreme Court power to promulgate rules concerning the protection and enforcement of constitutional rights. In the exercise of this power, the Supreme Court promulgated the Rule on the Writ of Amparo, the Rules on the Writ of Habeas Data, and the Rules of Procedure for Environmental Cases."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 124,
        "Question": "Congress enacted R.A. No. 14344 creating the City of Masuwerte which took effect on September 25, 2014. Section 23 of the law specifically exempts the City of Masuwerte from the payment of legal fees in the cases that it would file and/or prosecute in the courts of law. In two (2) cases that it filed, the City of Masuwerte was assessed legal fees by the clerk of court pursuant to Rule 141 (Legal Fees) of the Rules of Court. The City of Masuwerte questions the assessment claiming that it is exempt from paying legal fees under Section 23 of its charter. Is the claim of exemption tenable? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "The exemption from payment of legal fees is not valid. The rules promulgated by the Supreme Court for the payment of legal fees were in the exercise of its rule-making power cannot be modified by a law granting an exemption from payment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 125,
        "Question": "In her interview before the Judicial and Bar Council (JBC), Commissioner Annie Amorsolo of the National Labor Relations Commission claims that she should be given credit for judicial service because as NLRC Commissioner, she has the rank of a Justice of the Court of Appeals; she adjudicates cases that are appealable to the Court of Appeals; she is assigned car plate No. 10; and she is, by law, entitled to the rank, benefits and privileges of a Court of Appeals Justice. If you are a member of the JBC, would you give credit to this explanation? (6%)",
        "Answer": "No, I will not give credence to the explanation of Commissioner Annie Amorsolo. Her ranking merely means that she has the same salary and benefits as a Justice of the Court of Appeals. However, she is not actually a Justice of the Court of Appeals. The National labor Relations is not a court. She does not perform judicial functions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 126,
        "Question": "The 'Poverty Alleviation and Assistance Act 'was passed to enhance the capacity of the most marginalized families nationwide. A financial assistance scheme called .conditional cash transfers' was initially funded 500 million pesos by Congress. One of the provisions of the law gave the Joint-Congressional Oversight Committee authority to screen the list of beneficiary families initially determined by the Secretary of Department of Social Welfare and Development pursuant to the Department implementing rules. Mang Pandoy, a resident of Smokey Mountain in Tondo, questioned the authority of the Committee. Does Mang Pandoy have legal standing to question the law? ",
        "Answer": "On the assumption that Mang Pandoy is a beneficiary of the financial legal assistance, he has legal standing to question the law. He may be prejudiced by the improper screening of the beneficiary families. Besides, since the implementation of the law will require the expenditure of public funds, as a taxpayer Mang Pandoy has legal standing to question the law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 127,
        "Question": "Define: Doctrine of necessary implication ",
        "Answer": "The doctrine of necessary implication means that every statute is understood by implication to contain all such provisions as may be necessary to effectuate its object and purpose, or to make effective rights, powers, privileges or jurisdiction which it grants, including all such collateral and subsidiary consequences as may be fairly and logically inferred from its terms."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 128,
        "Question": "The provision under the Constitution — that any member who took no part, dissented, or inhibited from a decision or resolution must state the reason for his dissent or non-participation — applies _____. ",
        "Answer": "to the Supreme Court, the Court of Appeals, the Sandiganbayan and the Court of Tax Appeals"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 129,
        "Question": "A person who has a personal and substantial interest in the case, such that he has sustained, or will sustain, direct injury as a result of its enforcement is considered to have:",
        "Answer": "standing to challenge the governmental act."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 130,
        "Question": "Mr. Yellow and Mr. Orange were the leading candidates in the vicepresidential elections. After elections, Yellow emerged as the winner by a slim margin of 100,000 votes. Undaunted, Orange filed a protest with the Presidential Electoral Tribunal (PET). After due consideration of the facts and the issues, the PET ruled that Orange was the real winner of the elections and ordered his immediate proclamation. a. Aggrieved, Yellow filed with the Supreme Court a Petition for Certiorari challenging the decision of the PET alleging grave abuse of discretion. Does the Supreme Court have jurisdiction? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "A. The Supreme Court has no jurisdiction over the petition the presidential electoral tribunal is not simply an agency to which the members of the supreme court were assigned. It is not separate from the supreme court."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 131,
        "Question": "Courts may still decide cases that have otherwise become academic when they involve",
        "Answer": "petitions for habeas corpus."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 132,
        "Question": "The 'operative fact' doctrine of constitutional law is applied when a law is declared:",
        "Answer": "unconstitutional."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 133,
        "Question": "Define/explain: Doctrine of operative facts ",
        "Answer": "The doctrine of operative facts means that before a law was declared unconstitutional, its actual existence must be taken into account and whatever was done while the law was in operation should be recognized as valid."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 134,
        "Question": "When the Supreme Court nullified the decisions of the military tribunal for lack of jurisdiction, it excluded from their coverage decisions of acquittal where the defendants were deemed to have acquired a vested right. In so doing, the Supreme Court applied",
        "Answer": "the operative fact doctrine."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 135,
        "Question": "Courts may dismiss a case on ground of mootness when",
        "Answer": "the questioned law has been repealed."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 136,
        "Question": "Where there is 'the impossibility of a court's undertaking independent resolution without expressing lack of the respect due coordinate branches of government; or an unusual need for unquestioning adherence to a political decision already made; or the potentially of embarrassment from multifarious pronouncement by various departments on a question,' describes what kind of political question:",
        "Answer": "prudential kind."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 137,
        "Question": "According to Sec. 3, Art. VIII of the Constitution, the Judiciary shall enjoy fiscal autonomy. What does the term fiscal autonomy signify? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The fiscal autonomy of the Judiciary means that the appropriation for the Judiciary may not be reduced by Congress below the amount appropriated for the previous year, and after approval, shall be automatically and regularly released. Fiscal autonomy authorizes the Supreme Court to levy, assess and collect fees, and to determine how its funds should be utilized."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 138,
        "Question": "A judge of the Regional Trial Court derives his powers and duties from",
        "Answer": "statute."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 139,
        "Question": "Associate Justice A retires from the Supreme Court 90 days before the forthcoming Presidential election. May the incumbent President still appoint Justice A's successor?",
        "Answer": "Yes, vacancies in the Supreme Court should be filled within 90 days from occurrence of the vacancy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 140,
        "Question": "The President wants to appoint A to the vacant post of Associate Justice of the Supreme Court because of his qualifications, competence, honesty, and efficiency. But A's name is not on the list of nominees that the Judicial and Bar Council (JBC) submitted to the President. What should the President do?",
        "Answer": "Appoint from the list."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 141,
        "Question": "When the Supreme Court sits in division, cases can be decided by as few as a minimum of:",
        "Answer": "three votes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 142,
        "Question": "The Court had adopted the practice of announcing its decision in important, controversial or interesting cases the moment the votes had been taken among the justices, even as the final printed decision and separate opinions are not yet available to the public. In a greatly anticipated decision in a case of wide-ranging ramifications, the voting was close - 8 for the majority, while 7 were for the other side. After the Court had thus voted, it issued a press release announcing the result, with the advice that the printed copy of the decision, together with the separate opinions, were to be issued subsequently. The following day, however, one of the members of the Court died. The Court then announced that it would deliberate anew on the case since apparently the one who died belonged to the majority. Citizens for Transparency, a group of civic-spirited professionals and ordinary citizens dedicated to transparency and accountability in the government, questioned the act of the Court. The petitioners claimed the decision had already been validly adopted and promulgated. Therefore, it could no longer be recalled by the Court. At the same time, the group also asked the Court to disclose to the public the original decision and the separate opinions of the magistrates, together with what they had deliberated on just before they came up with the press release about the 8-7 decision. (A) Was the announced 8-7 decision already validly promulgated and thus not subject to recall?",
        "Answer": "A. The decision cannot be deemed to have been promulgated simply because of the announcement of the voting in a press release, because the decision has not yet been issued and filled with the Clerk of Court. Until the decision is filed with the Clerk of Court, the Justices still have control over the decision and they can still change their votes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 143,
        "Question": "Congress enacted a law providing for trial by jury for those charged with crime or offenses punishable by reclusion perpetua or lifeimprisonment. The law provides for the qualifications of members of the jury, the guidelines for the bar and bench for their selection, the manner a trial by jury shall operate, and the procedures to be followed. Is the law constitutional? (6%)",
        "Answer": "The law providing for trial by jury is unconstitutional because of the omission in Article VIII, Section 5 (5) of the 1987 Constitution of the provisions in Article VIII, Section 13 of the 1935 Constitution and Article X, Section 5(5) 1973 Constitution, which both authorized the Legislature to repeal, alter or supplement the rules of procedure promulgated by the Supreme Court. Congress can no longer enact any law governing rules of procedure for the courts."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 144,
        "Question": "Congress passed a law, R.A. No. 15005, creating an administrative Board principally tasked with the supervision and regulation of legal education. The Board was attached to the Department of Education. It was empowered, among others, to prescribe minimum standards for law admission and minimum qualifications of faculty members, the basic curricula for the course of study aligned to the requirements for admission to the Bar, law practice and social consciousness, as well as to establish a law practice internship as a requirement for taking the Bar which a law student shall undergo anytime during the law course, and to adopt a system of continuing legal education. Professor Boombas tick, a long-time law practitioner and lecturer in several prestigious law schools, assails the constitutionality of the law arguing that it encroached on the prerogatives of the Supreme Court to promulgate rules relative to admission to the practice of law, the Integrated Bar, and legal assistance to the underprivileged. If you were Professor Boombas tick’s understudy, how may you help him develop clear, concise and cogent arguments in support of his position based on the present Constitution and the decisions of the Supreme Court on judicial independence and fiscal autonomy? (2014 BAR)",
        "Answer": "The statutory authority granted to the administrative Board to promulgate rules and regulations cannot encroach upon the exclusive authority of the Supreme Court to regulate the admission to the practice of law. Thus, The Administrative Board cannot prescribe additional standards for admission to the practice of law, adopt a course study which is inconsistent with the requirements to take the bar examinations. Since Congress has no power to repeal, alter or supplement the Rules of Court, it cannot delegate such power to the Administrative Board."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 145,
        "Question": "A law fixing the passing grade in the Bar examinations at 70%, with no grade lower than 40% in any subject, is constitutional.",
        "Answer": "False. Such a law entails amendment of the Rules of Court promulgated by the Supreme Court. The present Constitution has taken away the power of Congress to alter the Rules of Court. The law will violate the principle of separation of powers."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 146,
        "Question": "Under Sec. 5, Article VIII of the Constitution, the Supreme Court shall have the power to 'promulgate rules concerning the protection and enforcement of constitutional rights, pleading, practice and procedure in all courts x x x7 Section 23 of RA. No. 9165 or the Comprehensive Dangerous Drugs Act of 2002 provides that ' any person charged under any provision of this Act regardless of the imposable penalty shall not be allowed to avail of the provision on plea-bargaining. Patricio, a user who was charged with alleged sale of shabu but who wants to enter a plea of guilty to a charge of possession, questions the constitutionality of Sec. 23 on the ground that Congress encroached on the rule-making power of the Supreme Court under Sec. 5, Article VIII. He argues that plea-bargaining is procedural in nature and is within the exclusive constitutional power of the Court. Is Patricio correct? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Patricio is not correct. Defining the penalty for a criminal offense involves the exercise of legislative power. When Section 23 of the Comprehensive Dangerous Drugs Act prohibited plea-bargaining, Congress defined what should be the penalty for the criminal offense. The power of the Supreme Court to promulgate rules of procedure is subject to the limitation that it should no modify substantive rights."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 147,
        "Question": "Judge Lloyd was charged with serious misconduct before the Supreme Court. The Court found him guilty and ordered him dismissed. Believing that the decision was not immediately executory, he decided a case that had been submitted for resolution. The decision became final and executory. But the losing party filed a certiorari action with the Court of Appeals seeking to annul the writ of execution issued in the case and bar Judge Lloyd from further acting as judge. Can the relief against Judge Lloyd be granted?",
        "Answer": "Yes, Judge Lloyd ’s right to stay as judge may be challenged as a necessary incident of the certiorari action."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 148,
        "Question": "Congress may increase the appellate jurisdiction of the Supreme Court: ",
        "Answer": "only with the advice and concurrence of the Supreme Court."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 149,
        "Question": "Patricio was elected member of the House of Representative in the May 2010 Elections. His opponent Jose questioned Patricio’s victory before the House of Representatives Electoral Tribunal and later with the Supreme Court. In the decision promulgated in November 2011, the Court ruled in Jose’s favor; thus, Patricio was ousted from his seat in Congress. Within a year from that decision, the President can appoint Patricio ______. ",
        "Answer": "to any position as no prohibition applies to Patricio."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 150,
        "Question": "The Civil Service shall be administered by the Civil Service Commission composed of a:",
        "Answer": "Chairman and two (2) Commissioners."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 151,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is NOT an independent Constitutional Commission under Article IX, Section 1 of the Constitution:",
        "Answer": "Commission on Human Rights."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 152,
        "Question": "The independent Constitutional Commissions enjoy:",
        "Answer": "decisional autonomy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 153,
        "Question": "Choose the least accurate statement about the independence guaranteed by the 1987 Constitution to the following constitutional bodies: ",
        "Answer": "The COMELEC, the COA, and the CSC enjoy the same degree of independence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 154,
        "Question": "Towards the end of the year, the Commission on Audit (COA) sought the remainder of its appropriation from the Department of Budget and Management (DBM). However, the DBM refused because the COA had not yet submitted a report on the expenditures relative to the earlier amount released to it. And, pursuant to the 'no report, no release' policy of the DBM, COA is not entitled to any further releases in the meantime. COA counters that such a policy contravenes the guaranty of fiscal autonomy granted by the Constitution. Is COA entitled to receive the rest of its appropriations even without complying with the DBM policy? ",
        "Answer": "Yes. COA is entitled to the rest of its appropriations even without complying with the DBM policy. That the no report, no release policy may not be validly enforced against offices vested with fiscal autonomy is not disputed. Indeed, such policy cannot be enforced against offices possessing fiscal autonomy without violating Article IX (A), Section 5 of the Constitution which provides: 'Sec. 5. The Commission shall enjoy fiscal autonomy. Their approved appropriations shall be automatically and regularly released.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 155,
        "Question": "Each of the Constitutional Commissions is expressly described as 'independent,' exemplified by its",
        "Answer": "fiscal autonomy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 156,
        "Question": "The Congress establishes by law Philippine Funds, Inc., a private corporation, to receive foreign donations coming from abroad during national and local calamities and disasters, and to enable the unhampered and speedy disbursements of the donations through the mere action of its Board of Directors. Thereby, delays in the release of the donated funds occasioned by the stringent rules of procurement would be avoided. Also, the releases would not come under the jurisdiction of the Commission on Audit (COA). Can the Congress pass the law that would exempt the foreign grants from the jurisdiction of the COA? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "Congress cannot exempt the foreign grants from the jurisdiction of the Commission on Audit. Its jurisdiction extends to all government-owned or controlled corporations, including those funded by donations through the Government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 157,
        "Question": "The Commission on Elections is an independent body tasked to enforce all laws relative to the conduct of elections. Hence, it may",
        "Answer": "authorize the citizens arm to use election returns for unofficial count."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 158,
        "Question": "The President appoints Emilio Melchor as Chairperson of the Civil Service Commission. Upon confirmation of Melchor’s appointment, the President issues an executive order including him as Ex-Officio member of the Board of Trustees of the Government Service Insurance System (GSIS), Employees Compensation Commission (ECC), and the Board of Directors of the Philippine Health Insurance Corporation (PHILHEALTH). Allegedly, this is based on the Administrative Code of 1997 (E.O. No. 292), particularly Section 14, Chapter 3, Title I-A, Book V. This provision reads: 'The chairman of the CSC shall be a member of the Board of Directors of other governing bodies of government entities whose functions affect the career development, employment, status, rights, privileges, and welfare of government officials and employees... ' A taxpayer questions the designation of Melchor as ex-officio member of the said corporations before the Supreme Court based on two (2) grounds, to wit: (1) it violates the constitutional prohibition on members of the Constitutional Commissions to hold any other office or employment during his tenure; and (2) it impairs the independence of the CSC. Will the petition prosper? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "(1) The Chairperson Emilio Melchor’s holding ex-officio of the other offices under the Executive Order mentioned in the problem would constitute a clear violation of the special prohibition in Section 2 of Article IX-A of the Constitution, which strictly provides that he shall, during his tenure, not hold any other office or employment. Said constitutional provision does not make any distinction among the offices he may not hold, or as to whether or not the functions attached to said offices would be primarily related to his duties as Chairperson of the Civil Service Commission and therefore may be held in an ex-officio capacity. The GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF are vested by their respective charters with various powers and functions to carry out the purposes for which they were created. While powers and functions associated with appointments, compensation and benefits affect the career development, employment status, rights, privileges, and welfare of government officials and employees, the GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF are also tasked to perform other corporate powers and functions that are not personnel-related. All of these powers and functions, whether personnel-related or not, are carried out and exercised by the respective Boards of the GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF. Hence, when the CSC Chairman sits as a member of the governing Boards of the GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF, he may exercise these powers and functions, which are not anymore derived from his position as CSC Chairman, such as imposing interest on unpaid or unremitted contributions, issuing guidelines for the accreditation of health care providers, or approving restructuring proposals in the payment of unpaid loan amortizations. The CSC Chairman’s designation as a member of the governing Boards of the GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF entitles him to receive per diem, a form of additional compensation that is disallowed by the concept of an ex officio position by virtue of its clear contravention of the proscription set by Section 2, Article IX-A of the 1987 Constitution. This situation goes against the principle behind an ex officio position, and must, therefore, be held unconstitutional. (1) Apart from violating the prohibition against holding multiple offices, Melchor’s designation as member of the governing Boards of the GSIS, PHILHEALTH, ECC and HDMF impairs the independence of the CSC. Under Section 17, Article VII of the Constitution, the President exercises control overall government offices in the Executive Branch. An office that is legally not under the control of the President is not part of the Executive Branch."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 159,
        "Question": "Professor Masipag who holds a plantilla or regular item in the University of the Philippines (UP) is appointed as an Executive Assistant in the Court of Appeals (CA). The professor is considered only on leave of absence in UP while he reports for work at the CA which shall pay him the salary of the Executive Assistant. The appointment to the CA position was questioned, but Professor Masipag countered that he will not collect the salary for both positions; hence, he can not be accused of receiving double compensation. Is the argument of the professor valid? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Although Professor Masipag is correct in saying that 'he cannot be accused of receiving double compensation' as he would not actually be receiving additional or double compensation, it is submitted that he may nevertheless not be allowed to accept the position of Executive Assistant of the Court of Appeals during his incumbency as a regular employee of the University of the Philippines, as the former would be an incompatible office not allowed to be concurrently held by him under the provisions of Article IX-B, Section 7 of the Constitution, the second paragraph of which species that 'unless otherwise allowed by law or by the primary functions of his position, no appointive official shall hold any other office in the Government.'"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 160,
        "Question": "What is the rotational scheme of appointments in the COMELEC? ",
        "Answer": "The rotational scheme of appointments in the Commissions on Elections refers to the scheme in which there is a regular recurrence of a two-year interval between the expiration of terms of the Chairman and the Commissioners."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 161,
        "Question": "What are the two conditions for its workability ",
        "Answer": "The two (2) conditions for the workability of the rotational scheme of appointments are the following: (1) the terms of the first Chairman and Commissioners should start on a common date, irrespective of variation of dates of their appointments and qualifications, and (2) any vacancy due to the death, resignation or disability before expiration of the term should be filled only for the unexpired balance of the term."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 162,
        "Question": "To what other constitutional offices does the rotational scheme of appointments apply? ",
        "Answer": "The rotational scheme of appointments applies also to the Judicial and Bar Council, the Civil Service Commission, and the Commission on Audit."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 163,
        "Question": "The Comelec en banc cannot hear and decide a case at first instance EXCEPT when",
        "Answer": "the inhibition of all the members of a Division is sought."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 164,
        "Question": "The COMELEC en banc shall decide a motion for reconsideration of",
        "Answer": "the decision of the COMELEC division involving an election protest."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 165,
        "Question": "A tax is progressive when:",
        "Answer": "the rate increases as the tax base increases."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 166,
        "Question": "The most essential, insistent and the least limitable of (government) powers, extending as it does to all the great public needs, is:",
        "Answer": "police power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 167,
        "Question": "The totality of governmental power is contained in three great powers:",
        "Answer": "police power, power of eminent domain, power of taxation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 168,
        "Question": "The price of staple goods like rice may be regulated for the protection of the consuming public through the exercise of",
        "Answer": "police power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 169,
        "Question": "The city government filed a complaint for expropriation of 10 lots to build a recreational complex for the members of the homeowners' association of Sitio Sto. Tomas, the most populated residential compound in the city. The lot owners challenged the purpose of the expropriation. Does the expropriation have a valid purpose?",
        "Answer": "Yes, it serves the well-being of the local residents."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 170,
        "Question": "When the State requires private cemeteries to reserve 10% of their lots for burial of the poor, it exercises its",
        "Answer": "police power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 171,
        "Question": "The government sought to expropriate a parcel of land belonging to Y. The law provides that, to get immediate possession of the land, the government must deposit the equivalent of the land's zonal value. The government insisted, however, that what apply are the rules of court which require an initial deposit only of the assessed value of the property. Which should prevail on this matter, the law or the rules of court?",
        "Answer": "The law should prevail since the right to just compensation is a substantive right that Congress has the power to define."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 172,
        "Question": "To address the pervasive problem of gambling, Congress is considering the following options: (1) prohibit all forms of gambling; (2) allow gambling only on Sundays; (3) allow gambling only in government-owned casinos; and (4) remove all prohibitions against gambling but impose a tax equivalent to 30% on all winnings. If Congress chooses the first option and passes the corresponding law absolutely prohibiting all forms of gambling, can the law be validly attacked on the ground that it is an invalid exercise of police power? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "The law absolutely prohibiting all forms of gambling is a valid exercise of police power, because it is an evil that undermines the social, moral and economic growth of the nation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 173,
        "Question": "The Metropolitan Manila Development Authority is authorized to confiscate a driver's' license in the enforcement of traffic regulations. (0.5%)",
        "Answer": "The statement that the Metropolitan Manila Development Authority is authorized to confiscate a driver's license in the enforcement of traffic regulations is false. Since Republic Act No. 7924 does not grant the Metropolitan Manila Development Authority the authority to enact ordinances, the grant to it by Section 5(f) of Republic Act No. 7924 of the power to confiscate drivers' licenses without the need of any other law is an unauthorized exercise of police power."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 174,
        "Question": "X, a Filipino and Y, an American, both teach at the International Institute in Manila. The institute gave X a salary rate of P1,000 per hour and Y, P1,250 per hour plus housing, transportation, shipping costs, and leave travel allowance. The school cited the dislocation factor and limited tenure of Y to justify his high salary rate and additional benefits. The same package was given to the other foreign teachers. The Filipino teachers assailed such differential treatment, claiming it is discriminatory and violates the equal protection clause. Decide.",
        "Answer": "The distinction is fair considering the burden of teaching abroad."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 175,
        "Question": "On November 7, 1990, nine lawyers of the Legal Department of Y Bank who were all under Fred Torre, sent a complaint to management accusing Torre of abusive conduct and mismanagement. Furnished with a copy of the complaint, Torre denied the charges. Two days later, the lawyers and Torre were called to a conference in the office of the Board Chairman to give their respective sides of the controversy. However, no agreement was reached thereat. Bank Director Romulo Moret was tasked to look further into the matter. He met with the lawyers together with Torre several times but to no avail. Moret then submitted a report sus-taining the charges of the lawyers. The Board Chairman wrote Torre to inform him that the bank had chosen the compassionate option of 'waiting' for Torre’s resignation. Torre was asked, without being dismissed, to turn over the documents of all cases handled by him to another official of the bank but Torre refused to resign and requested for a 'full hearing'. Days later, he reiterated his request for a 'full hearing', claiming that he had been 'constructively dismissed'. Moret assured Torre that he is 'free to remain in the employ of the bank' even if he has no particular work assignment. After another request for a 'full hearing' was ignored, Torre filed a complaint with the arbitration branch of NLRC for illegal dismissal. Reacting thereto, the bank terminated the services of Torre. Questions: Was Torre 'constructively dismissed' before he filed his complaint? Given the multiple meetings held among the bank officials, the lawyers and Torre, is it correct for him to say that he was not given an opportunity to be heard? Explain your answers. ",
        "Answer": "Torre was constructively dismissed, as held in Equitable Banking Corporation v. National Labor Relations Commission, 273 SCRA 352. Allowing an employee to report for work without being assigned any work constitutes constructive dismissal. Torre is correct in saying that he was not given the chance to be heard. The meetings in the nature of consultations and conferences cannot be considered as valid substitutes for the proper observance of notice and hearing."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 176,
        "Question": "A law interfering with the rights of the person meets the requirements of substantive due process when",
        "Answer": "the interest of the general public, as distinguished from those of a particular case, requires such interference."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 177,
        "Question": "On April 6, 1963, Police Officer Mario Gatdula was charged by the Mayor with Grave Misconduct and Violation of Law before the Municipal Board. The Board investigated Gatdula but before the case could be decided, the City charter was approved. The City Fiscal, citing Section 30 of the city charter, asserted that he was authorized thereunder to investigate city officers and employees. The case against Gatdula was then forwarded to him, and a re-investigation was conducted. The office of the Fiscal subsequently recommended dismissal. On January 11, 1966, the City Mayor returned the records of the case to the City Fiscal for the submission of an appropriate resolution but no resolution was submitted. On March 3,-1968, the City Fiscal transmitted the records to the City Mayor recommending that final action thereon be made by the City Board of Investigators (CBI). Although the CBI did not conduct an investigation, the records show that both the Municipal Board and the Fiscal’s Office exhaustively heard the case with both parties afforded ample opportunity to adduce their evidence and argue their cause. The Police Commission found Gatdula guilty on the basis of the records forwarded by the CBI. Gatdula challenged the adverse decision o'f the Police Commission theorizing that he was deprived of due process. Questions: Is the Police Commission bound by the findings of the City Fiscal? Is Gatdula’s protestation of lack or non- observance of due process well-grounded? Explain your answers. ",
        "Answer": "The Police Commission is not bound by the findings of the City Fiscal. In Mangubat v. de Castro, 163 SCRA 608, it was held that the Police Commission is not prohibited from making its own findings on the basis of its own evaluation of the records. Likewise, the protestation of lack of due process is not well-grounded, since the hearings before the Municipal Board and the City Fiscal offered Gatdula the chance to be heard. There is no denial of due process if the decision was rendered on the basis of evidence contained in the record and disclosed to the parties affect"
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 178,
        "Question": "A criminal statute that 'fails to give a person of ordinary intelligence fair notice that his contemplated conduct is forbidden by statute' is:",
        "Answer": "void for vagueness."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 179,
        "Question": "Jojo filed a criminal complaint against Art for theft of a backpack worth P150.00 with the Office of the City Prosecutor of Manila. The crime is punishable with arresto mayor to prison correctional in its minimum period, or not to exceed 4 years and 2 months. The case was assigned to .Prosecutor Tristan and he applied Sec. 8(a) of Rule 112 which reads: '(a) If filed with the prosecutor. If the complaint is filed directly with the prosecutor involving an offense punishable by imprisonment of less than four (4) years, two (2) months and one (1) day, the procedure outlined in Sec. 3(a) of this Rule shall be observed. The Prosecutor shall act on the complaint within ten (10) days from its filing.' On the other hand, Sec. 3(a) of Rule 112 provides: '(a) The complaint shall state the address of the respondent and shall be accompanied by affidavits of the complainant and his witnesses as well as other supporting documents to establish probable cause. x x x Since Sec. 8(a) authorizes the Prosecutor to decide the complaint on the basis of the affidavits and other supporting documents submitted by the complainant, Prosecutor Tristan did not notify Art nor require him to submit a counter-affidavit. He proceeded to file the Information against Art with the Metropolitan Trial Court. Art vehemently assails Sec. 8(a) of Rule 112 as unconstitutional and violative of due process and his rights as an accused under the Constitution for he was not informed of the complaint nor was he given the opportunity to raise his defenses thereto before the Information was filed. Rule on the constitutionality of Sec. 8(a) of Rule 112. Explain. ",
        "Answer": "The contention of Art is not meritorious. The right to be informed of the complaint and to be given the opportunity to raise ones defenses does not apply to preliminary investigation. Preliminary investigation is merely procedural. It may be dispensed with without violating the right of the accused to due process."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 180,
        "Question": "What do you understand by the term 'heirarchy of civil liberties'? Explain.",
        "Answer": "A. The hierarchy of civil liberties means that freedom of expression and the rights of peaceful assembly are superior to property rights."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 181,
        "Question": "In the hierarchy of civil liberties, which right occupies the highest preferred position:",
        "Answer": "right to freedom of expression and of assembly."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 182,
        "Question": "Compare and contrast 'overbreadth doctrine' from 'void-for-vagueness' doctrine. ",
        "Answer": "While the overbreadth doctrine decrees that a governmental purpose may not be achieved by means in a statute which sweep unnecessary broadly and thereby invades the area of protected freedom. A statute is void for vagueness when it forbids or requires the doing of an act in terms so vague that men of common intelligence cannot necessarily guess at its meaning and differ as to its application."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 183,
        "Question": "An ordinance prohibits 'notorious street gang members' from loitering in public places. The police are to disperse them or, if they refuse, place them under arrest. The ordinance enumerates which police officers can make arrest and defines street gangs, membership in them, and public areas. The ordinance was challenged for being vague regarding the meaning of 'notorious street gang members.' Is the ordinance valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, it is sufficiently clear for the public to know what acts it prohibits."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 184,
        "Question": "The void-for-vagueness doctrine is a concept which means that: ",
        "Answer": "if a law is incomprehensible to ordinary people such that they do not really know what is required or prohibited, then the law must be struck down."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 185,
        "Question": "A law is passed intended to protect women and children from all forms of violence. When a woman perceives an act to be an act of violence or a threat of violence against her, she may apply for a Barangay Protection Order (BP0) to be issued by the Barangay Chairman, which shall have the force and effect of law. Conrado, against whom a BP0 had been issued on petition of his wife, went to court to challenge the constitutionality of the law. He raises the following grounds: (A) The law violates the equal protection clause, because while it extends protection to women who may be victims of violence by their husbands, it does not extend the same protection to husbands who may be battered by their wives. (25%)",
        "Answer": "The law does not violate the equal protection clause. It is based on substantial distinctions. The unequal power relationship between women and men, the greater likelihood for women than men to be victims of violence, and the widespread gender bias and prejudice against women all make for real differences."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 186,
        "Question": "The Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Youth Association (GBTYA), an organization of gay, bisexual, and transgender persons, filed for accreditation with the COMELEC to join the forthcoming party-list elections. The COMELEC denied the application for accreditation on the ground that GBTY A espouses immorality which offends religious dogmas. GBTY A challenges the denial of its application based on moral grounds because it violates its right to equal protection of the law. b. Which of the three (3) levels of test should be applied to the present case? Explain.",
        "Answer": "b. Classification on the basis of sexual orientation is a quasi-subject classification that prompts intermediate review. Sexual orientation has no relation to a person’s ability to contribute to society. The discrimination that distinguishes the gays and lesbian persons are beyond their control. The group lacks sufficient political strength to bring an end to discrimination through political mean."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 187,
        "Question": "The equal protection clause allows valid classification of subjects that applies",
        "Answer": "for as long as the problem to be corrected exists."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 188,
        "Question": "Pornographic materials in the form of tabloids, magazines and other printed materials, proliferate and are being sold openly in the streets of Masaya City. The city Mayor organized a task force which confiscated these materials. He then ordered that the materials be burned in public. Dominador, publisher of the magazine, 'Plaything', filed a suit, raising the following constitutional issues: (a) the confiscation of the materials constituted an illegal search and seizure, because the same was done without a valid search warrant and (b) the Confiscation, as well as the proposed destruction of the materials, is a denial of the right to disseminate information, and thus, violates the constitutional right to freedom of expression. Is either or both contentions proper? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "(a) The confiscation of the materials constituted an illegal search and seizure, because it was done without a valid search warrant. It cannot be justified as a valid warrantless search and seizure, because such search and seizure must have been an incident of a lawful arrest. There was no lawful arrest. (b) The argument of Dominador that pornographic materials are protected by the constitutional right to freedom of expression is erroneous, Obscenity is not protected expression. Section 2 of Presidential Decree No. 969 requires the forfeiture and destruction of pornographic materials."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 189,
        "Question": "Ernesto, a minor, while driving a motor vehicle, was stopped at a mobile checkpoint. Noticing that Ernesto is a minor, ,SP01 Jojo asked Ernesto to exhibit his driver's license but Ernesto failed to produce it. $1301 Jojo requested Ernesto to alight from the vehicle and the latter acceded. Upon observing a bulge in the pants of Ernesto, the policeman frisked him and found an unlicensed .22-caliber pistol inside Ernesto's right pocket. Ernesto was arrested, detained and charged. At the trial, Ernesto, through his lawyer, argued that, policemen at mobile checkpoints are empowered to conduct nothing more than a 'visual search'. They cannot order the persons riding the vehicle to alight. They cannot frisk, or conduct a body search of the driver or the passengers of the vehicle. Ernesto's lawyer this posited that: (A) The search conducted in violation of the Constitution and established jurisprudence was an illegal search; thus, the gun which was seized in the course of an illegal search is the 'fruit of the poisonous tree' and is inadmissible in evidence. ",
        "Answer": "The warrantless search of motor vehicles at checkpoints should be limited to a visual search. Its occupants should not be subjected to a body search. The 'stop and frisk rule' applies when a police officer observes suspicious activity or unusual activity which may lead him to believe that a criminal act may be afoot. The 'stop and frisk' is merely a limited protective search of outer clothing for weapons."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 190,
        "Question": "Around 12:00 midnight, a team of police officers was on routine patrol in Barangay Makatarungan when it noticed an open delivery van neatly covered with banana leaves. Believing that the van was loaded with contraband, the team leader flagged down the vehicle which was driven by Hades. He inquired from Hades what was loaded on the van. Hades just gave the police officer a blank stare and started to perspire profusely. The police officers then told Hades that they will look inside the vehicle. Hades did not make any reply. The police officers then lifted the banana leaves and saw several boxes. They opened the boxes and discovered several kilos of shabu inside. Hades was charged with illegal possession of illegal drugs.   After due proceedings, he was convicted by the trial court. On appeal, the Court of Appeals affirmed his conviction. In his final bid for exoneration, Hades went to the Supreme Court claiming that his constitutional right against unreasonable searches and seizures was violated when the police officers searched his vehicle without a warrant; that the shabu confiscated from him is thus inadmissible in evidence; and that there being no evidence against him, he is entitled to an acquittal. For its part, the People of the Philippines maintains that the case of Hades involved a consented warrantless search which is legally recognized. The People adverts to the fact that Hades did not offer any protest when the police officers asked him if they could look inside the vehicle. Thus, any evidence obtained in the course thereof is admissible in evidence. Whose claim is correct? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The warrantless search was illegal. There was no probable cause to search the van. The shabu was not immediately apparent. It was discovered only after they opened the boxes. The mere passive silence of Hades did not constitute consent to the warrantless search."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 191,
        "Question": "Using the description of the supplier of shabu given by persons who had been arrested earlier for selling it, the police conducted a surveillance of the area indicated. When they saw a man who fitted the description walking from the apartment to his car, they approached and frisked him and he did not object. The search yielded an unlicensed gun tucked on his waist and shabu in his car. Is the search valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the police acted on reliable information which proved correct when they searched the man and his car."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 192,
        "Question": "An informer told the police that a Toyota Car with plate ABC 134 would deliver an unspecified quantity of ecstacy in Forbes Park, Makati City. The officers whom the police sent to watch the Forbes Park gates saw the described car and flagged it down. When the driver stopped and lowered his window, an officer saw a gun tucked on the driver's waist. The officer asked the driver to step out and he did. When an officer looked inside the car, he saw many tablets strewn on the driver's seat. The driver admitted they were ecstacy. Is the search valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the police acted based on reliable information and the fact that an officer saw the driver carrying a gun."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 193,
        "Question": "Crack agents of the Manila Police Anti-Narcotics Unit were on surveillance of a cemetery where the sale and use of prohibited drugs were rumored to be rampant. The team saw a man with reddish and glassy eyes walking unsteadily towards them, but he immediately veered away upon seeing the policemen. The team approached the man, introduced themselves as peace officers, then asked what he had in his clenched fist. Because the man refused to answer, a policeman pried the fist open and saw a plastic sachet filled with crystalline substance. The team then took the man into custody and submitted the contents of the sachet to forensic examination. The crystalline substance in the sachet turned out to be shabu. The man was accordingly charged in court. During the trial, the accused: Challenged the validity of his arrest;  and",
        "Answer": "The warrantless arrest of the accused was valid. The cemetery was rumored to be a place where the sale of drugs was rampant. The eyes of the accused were reddish and glassy. He was walking unsteadily, veered away from the policemen upon seeing them, and refused to say what was in his clenched fist. The policemen had sufficient reason to stop him and investigate if he was high on drugs. Since the investigation showed that the accused was in possession of shabu, he could be arrested without the need for a warrant."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 194,
        "Question": "In what scenario is an extensive search of moving vehicles without warrant valid?",
        "Answer": "The driver sped away in his car when the police flagged him down at a checkpoint."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 195,
        "Question": "A witnessed two hooded men with baseball bats enter the house of their next door neighbor B. After a few seconds, he heard B shouting, 'Huwag Pilo babayaran kita agad. Then Asaw the two hooded men hitting B until the latter fell lifeless. The assailants escaped using a yellow motorcycle with a fireball sticker on it toward the direction of an exclusive village nearby. A reported the incident to POI Nuval. The following day, POI Nuval saw the motorcycle parked in the garage of a house at Sta. Ines Street inside the exclusive village. He inquired with the caretaker as to who owned the motorcycle. The caretaker named the brothers Pilo and Ramon Maradona who were then outside the country. POI Nuval insisted on getting inside the garage. Out of fear, the caretaker allowed him. POI Nuval took 2 ski masks and 2 bats beside the motorcycle. Was the search valid? What about the seizure? Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The warrantless search and the seizure was not valid. It was not made as an incident to a lawful warranties arrest. The caretaker had no authority to waive the right of the brothers Pilo and Ramon Maradona to waive their right against an unreasonable search and seizure. The warrantless seizure of the ski masks and bats cannot be justified under the plain view doctrine, because they were seized after an invalid intrusion into the house."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 196,
        "Question": "Where a police officer observes unusual conduct which leads him reasonably to conclude in light of his experience that criminal activity may be afoot and that the persons with whom he is dealing may be armed and dangerous and he identifies himself and makes reasonable inquiries, but nothing serves to dispel his reasonable fear for his own or other’s safety, he is entitled to conduct a carefully limited search of the outer clothing of such persons for weapons. Such search is constitutionally permissible and is known as a:",
        "Answer": "stop and frisk."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 197,
        "Question": "When can evidence 'in plain view' be seized without need of a search warrant? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "Evidence in plain view can be seized without need of a search warrant if the following elements are present. 1. There was a prior valid intrusion based on the valid warrantless arrest in which the police were legally present pursuant of their duties; 2. The evidence was inadvertently discovered by the police who had the right to be where they were: 3. The evidence must be immediately apparent; and 4. Plain view justified seizure of the evidence without further search."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 198,
        "Question": "It is form of entrapment. The method is for an officer to pose as a buyer. He, however, neither instigates nor induces the accused to commit a crime because in these cases, the 'seller' has already decided to commit a crime. The offense happens right before the eyes of the officer. Under these circumstances:",
        "Answer": "there is no need for a warrant either for the seizure of the goods or for the arrest of the offender."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 199,
        "Question": "Paragraphs c, d and f of Section 36 of Republic Act No. 9165 provide: 'Sec. 36. Authorized drug testing, x x x The following shall be subjected to undergo drug testing: x x x. c. Students of secondary and tertiary schools x x x; d. Officers and employees of public and private offices x x x;. f. All persons charged before the prosecutor's office with a criminal offense having an imposable imprisonment of not less than 6 years and 1 day;' Petitioners contend that the assailed portions of Sec. 36 are unconstitutional for violating the right to privacy, the right against unreasonable searches and seizures and the equal protection clause. Decide if the assailed provisions are unconstitutional. ",
        "Answer": "The drug testing of students of secondary and tertiary schools is valid. Deterring their use of drugs by random drug testing is as important as enhancing efficient enforcement. Random drug testing of officers and employees of public and private officers is justifiable. Their expectation of privacy in office is reduced. The drug tests and results are kept confidential. Random drug testing is an effective way of deterring drug use and is reasonable. Public officials and employees are required by the Constitution to be accountable at all times to the people and to serve them with utmost responsibility and efficiency. The mandatory testing of all persons charged before the prosecutor’s office of a criminal offense punishable with imprisonment of at least six years and one day is void. They are not randomly picked and are not beyond suspicions. They do not consent to the procedure or waive their right to privacy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 200,
        "Question": "Under Article III, Section 2 of the Bill of Rights, which provides for the exclusion of evidence that violate the right to privacy of communication and correspondence, to come under the exclusionary rule, the evidence must be obtained by:",
        "Answer": "government agents."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 201,
        "Question": "In a criminal prosecution for murder, the prosecution presented, as witness, an employee of the Manila Hotel who produced in court a videotape recording showing the heated exchange between the accused and the victim that took place at the lobby of the hotel barely 30 minutes before the killing. The accused objects to the admission of the videotape recording on the ground that it was taken without his knowledge or consent, in violation of his right to privacy and the Anti- Wire Tapping law. Resolve the objection with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "The objection should be overruled. What the law prohibits is the overhearing, intercepting, and recording of private communications. Since the exchange of heated words was not private, its videotape recording is not prohibited."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 202,
        "Question": "The privacy of communication and correspondence shall be inviolable except upon lawful order of the court or when",
        "Answer": "public safety or order requires otherwise as prescribed by law."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 203,
        "Question": "An example of a content based restraint on free speech is a regulation prescribing",
        "Answer": "calibrated response to rallies that have become violent."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 204,
        "Question": "Executive Secretary Chua issued an order prohibiting the holding of rallies along Mendiola because it hampers the traffic flow to Malacanang. A group of militants questioned the order for being unconstitutional and filed a case against Secretary Chua to restrain him from enforcing the order. Secretary Chua raised state immunity from suit claiming that the state cannot be sued without its consent. Is the claim correct?",
        "Answer": "No, public officers may be sued to restrain him from enforcing an act claimed to be unconstitutional."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 205,
        "Question": "'Chilling effect' is a concept used in the area of constitutional litigation affecting:",
        "Answer": "protected speech."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 206,
        "Question": "In a protest rally’ along Padre Faura Street, Manila, Pedrong Pula took up the stage and began shouting 'kayong mga kurakot kayo! Magsi-resign na kayo! Kung hindi, manggugulo kami dito!' ('you corrupt officials, you better resign now, or else we will cause trouble here!') simultaneously, he brought out a rock the size of a- fist and pretended to hurl it at the flagpole area of a government building. He did not actually throw the rock. a. Police officers who were monitoring the situation immediately approached Pedrong Pula and arrested him. He was prosecuted for seditious speech and was convicted. On appeal, Pedrong Pula argued he was merely exercising his freedom of speech and freedom of expression guaranteed by the Bill of Rights. Decide with reasons. ",
        "Answer": "A. Pedrong Pula should be acquitted, his freedom of speech should not be limited in the absence of a clear and present danger of a substantive evil that the state had the right to prevent. He pretended to hurl a rock but did not actually throw it. He did not commit any act of lawless violence."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 207,
        "Question": "The complementing regime that best characterizes the guarantees of freedom of speech and of the press are:",
        "Answer": "no prior restraint and subsequent punishment."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 208,
        "Question": "Surveys Galore is an outfit involved in conducting nationwide surveys. In one such survey, it asked the people about the degree of trust and confidence they had in several institutions of the government. When the results came in, the judiciary was shown to be less trusted than most of the government offices. The results were then published by the mass media. Assension, a trial court judge, felt particularly offended by the news. He then issued a show-cause order against Surveys Galore directing the survey entity to explain why it should not be cited in contempt for coming up with such a survey and publishing the results which were so unflattering and degrading to the dignity of the judiciary. Surveys Galore immediately assailed the show-cause order of Judge Assension, arguing that it is violative of the constitutional guaranty of freedom of expression. Is Surveys Galore’s petition meritorious? ",
        "Answer": "Yes. Surveys Galore’s petition is meritorious. Unwarranted attacks on the dignity of the courts cannot be disguised as free speech, for the exercise of said right cannot be used to impair the independence and efficiency of courts or public respect therefore and confidence therein . Without the sub judice rule and the contempt power, the courts will be powerless to protect their integrity and independence that are essential in the orderly and effective dispensation and administration of justice. This, of course, is not meant to stifle all forms of criticism against the court. As the third branch of the government, the courts remain accountable to the people. The peoples freedom to criticize the government includes the right to criticize the courts, their proceedings and decisions. This is the principle of open justice, which is fundamental to our democratic society and ensures that (a) there is a safeguard against judicial arbitrariness or idiosyncrasy, and that (b) the publics confidence in the administration of justice is maintained.[ The criticism must, however, be fair, made in good faith, and not spill over the walls of decency and propriety. And to enhance the open court principle and allow the people to make fair and reasoned criticism of the courts, the sub judice rule excludes from its coverage fair and accurate reports (without comment) of what have actually taken place in open court. In sum, the court, in a pending litigation, must be shielded from embarrassment or influence in its all-important duty of deciding the case. Any publication pending a suit, reflecting upon the court, the parties, the officers of the court, the counsel, etc., with reference to the suit, or tending to influence the decision of the controversy, is contempt of court and is punishable. The resulting (but temporary) curtailment of speech because of the sub judice rule is necessary and justified by the more compelling interests to uphold the rights of the accused and promote the fair and orderly administration of justice. However, in the cae of Surveys Galore there is no pending case before the court. Thus, the subjudice rule does not apply. Surveys Galore’s petition is meritorious."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 209,
        "Question": "The guarantee of freedom of expression signifies: ",
        "Answer": "freedom from prior restraint."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 210,
        "Question": "a. What is the doctrine of 'overbreath'? In what context can it be correctly applied? Not correctly applied? Explain  b. What is the doctrine of 'void for vagueness'? In what context can it be correctly applied? Not correctly applied? Explain ",
        "Answer": "a. A Statement Is Overbroad When A Governmental Purpose To Control Or Prevent Activities Constitutionally Subject To State Regulations Is Sought To Be Achieved By Means Which Sweep Unnecessarily Broadly And Invade The Area Of Protected Freedom. It Applies Both To Free Speech Case And Penal Statutes. However, A Facial Challenge On The Ground Of Overbreadth Can Only Be Made In Free Speech Cases Because Of Its Chilling Effect Upon Protected Speech. A Facial Challenge On The Ground Of Overbreadth Is Not Applicable To Challenge On The Ground Of Overbreadth Is Not Applicable To Penal Statutes, Because In General They Have An In Terrorem Effect. b. A Statute Is Vague When It Lacks Comprehensible Standards That Men Of Common Intelligence That Guess Its Meaning And Differ As To Its Application. Its Applies To Both Free Speech Cases And Penal Statues. However, A Facial Challenge On The Ground Of Vagueness Can Be Made Only In Free Speech Cases. It Does Not Apply To Penal Statutes."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 211,
        "Question": "In keeping with the modern age of instant and incessant information and transformation, Congress passed Cybercrime Prevention Act to regulate access to and use of the amenities of the cyberspace. While ostensibly the law is intended to protect the interests of society, some of its provisions were also seen as impermissibly invading and impairing widely cherished liberties of the people particularly the freedom of expression. Before the law could even be implemented, petitions were filed in the Supreme Court questioning said provisions by people who felt threatened, for themselves as well as for the benefit of others who may be similarly affected but not minded enough to challenge the law. The Solicitor General countered that there is no basis for the exercise of the power of judicial review since there has yet been no violation of the law, and therefore, there is no actual case or controversy to speak of, aside from the fact that the petitioners have no locus standi since they do not claim to be in imminent danger of being prosecuted under the law. Can the Court proceed to decide the case even if the law has not yet become effective? ",
        "Answer": "The Supreme Court can proceed to decide the case even if the law has not yet become effective. Since the petitions filed sought to nullify the Cybercrime Prevention Act, Because it violated several provisions of the Bill of Rights, the Supreme Court became duty-bound to settle the dispute. Since it is alleged that the Cybercrime Prevention Act violates various provisions of the Bill of Rights, including freedom of speech, freedom of the press, and the right against unreasonable searches and seizures, the issues raised are of paramount public interest of transcendental importance and with far-reaching constitutional implications that justify dispensation with locus standi and exercise of the power of judicial review by the Supreme Court. Jurisprudence provides that locus standi is not required when the action was filed to prevent a chilling effect on the exercise of the right to freedom of expression and overbreadth."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 212,
        "Question": "The overbreadth doctrine posits that the government: ",
        "Answer": "the government is prohibited in banning unprotected speech if a substantial amount of protected speech is restrained or chilled in the process."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 213,
        "Question": "When is a facial challenge to the constitutionality of a law on the ground of violation of the Bill of Rights traditionally allowed? Explain your answer. ",
        "Answer": "In United States (US) constitutional law, a facial challenge, also known as a First Amendment Challenge, is one that is launched to assail the validity of statues concerning not only protected speech, but also all other rights in the First Amendment. This include religious freedom, freedom of the press, and the rights of the people to peaceably assemble, and to petition the Government for a redress of grievances. After all, the fundamental right to religious freedom, freedom of the press and peaceful assembly are but component rights of the right to one’s freedom of expression, as they are modes which one’s thoughts are externalized. In this jurisdiction, the application of doctrines originating from the U.S. has been generally maintained, albeit with some modifications. While this Court has withheld the application of facial challenges to strictly penal statues, it has expanded its scope to cover statues not only regulating free speech, but also those involving religious freedom, and other fundamentals rights. The underlying reason for this modification is simple. For unlike its counterpart in the U.S., this Court, under its expanded jurisdiction, is mandated by the Fundamental Law not only to settle actual controversies involving rights which are legally demandable and enforceable, but also to determine whether or not there has been a grave abuse of discretion amounting to lack or excess of jurisdiction on the part of any branch or instrumentality of the Government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 214,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not a proper test in cases of challenges to governmental acts that may violate protected speech:",
        "Answer": "dangerous tendency."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 215,
        "Question": "Commercial speech is entitled to:",
        "Answer": "lesser protection compared to other constitutionally guaranteed expression."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 216,
        "Question": "In a protest rally’ along Padre Faura Street, Manila, Pedrong Pula took up the stage and began shouting 'kayong mga kurakot kayo! Magsi-resign na kayo! Kung hindi, manggugulo kami dito!' ('you corrupt officials, you better resign now, or else we will cause trouble here!') simultaneously, he brought out a rock the size of a- fist and pretended to hurl it at the flagpole area of a government building. He did not actually throw the rock. b. What is 'commercial speech'? Is it entitled to constitutional protection? What must be shown in order for government to curtail 'commercial speech'? Explain. ",
        "Answer": "B. Commercial speech is communication which involves only the commercial interests of the speaker and the audience such as advertisements. Commercial speech is entitled to constitutional protection. Commercial speech may be required to be submitted to a government agency for review to protect public interest by preventing false or deceptive claims."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 217,
        "Question": "No liability can attach to a false, defamatory statement if it relates to official conduct, unless the public official concerned proves that the statement was with knowledge that it was false or with reckless disregard of whether it was false or not. This is known as what rule?",
        "Answer": "actual malice rule."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 218,
        "Question": "In the law of libel and protected speech, a person who, by his accomplishments, fame, or mode of living, or by adopting a profession or calling which gives the public a legitimate interest in his doings, his affairs, and his character, has become a:",
        "Answer": "public figure."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 219,
        "Question": "Fernando filed an administrative complaint against his co-teacher, Amelia, claiming that the latter is living with a married man who is not her husband. Fernando charged Amelia with committing 'disgraceful and immoral conduct' in violation of the Revised Administrative Code and, thus, should not be allowed to remain employed in the government. Amelia, on the other hand, claims that she and her partner are members of a religious sect that allows members of the congregation who have been abandoned by their respective spouses to enter marital relations under a Declaration of Pleading Faithfulness.' Having made such Declaration, she argues that she cannot be charged with committing immoral conduct for she is entitled to free exercise of religion under the Constitution. (B) Briefly explain the concept of 'benevolent neutrality.' ",
        "Answer": "Benevolent neutrality means that with respect to governmental actions, accommodation of religion may be permitted to allow individuals and groups to exercise their religion without hindrance. What is sought is not a declaration of unconstitutionality of the law but an exemption from its application."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 220,
        "Question": "Section 28, Title VI, Chapter 9, of the Administrative Code of 1987 requires all educational institutions to observe a simple and dignified flag ceremony, including the playing or singing of the Philippine National Anthem, pursuant to rules to be promulgated by the Secretary of Education Culture and Sports. The refusal of a teacher, student or pupil to attend or participate in the flag ceremony is a ground for dismissal after due investigation. The Secretary of Education, Culture and Sports issued a memorandum implementing said provision of law. As ordered, the flag ceremony would be held on Mondays at 7:30 a.m, during class days. A group of teachers, students and pupils requested the Secretary that they be exempted from attending the flag ceremony on the ground that attendance thereto was against their religious belief. The Secretary denied the request. The teachers, students and pupils concerned went to Court to have the memorandum circular declared null and void. Decide the case.",
        "Answer": "The teachers and the students should be exempted from the flag ceremony. As held in Ebrahnaq vs. Division Superintendent of Schools of Cebu. 251 SCRA 569, to compel them to participate in the flag ceremony will violate their freedom of religion. Freedom of religion cannot be impaired except upon the showing of a clear and present danger of a substantive evil which the State has a right to prevent. The refusal of the teachers and the students to participate in the flag ceremony does not pose a clear and present danger."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 221,
        "Question": "To instill religious awareness in the students of Doña Trinidad High School, a public school in Bulacan, the Parent Teacher’s Association of the school contributed funds for the construction of a grotto and chapel where ecumenical religious services and seminars are being held after school hours. The use of the school grounds for these purposes was questioned by a parent who does not belong to any religious group. As his complaint was not addressed by the school, officials, he filed and administrative complaint against the principal before the DECS is the principal liable? Explain briefly. ",
        "Answer": "The principal is liable. Although the grotto and the chapel can be used by different religious sects without discrimination, the land occupied by the grotto and the chapel will be permanently devoted to religious use without being required to pay rent. This violates the prohibition against the establishment of religion enshrine in Section 5 of the Bill of Rights. Although religion is allowed to be taught in public elementary and high schools, it should be without additional cost to the government."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 222,
        "Question": "The free exercise and non-establishment clauses pertain to which right under the Bill of Rights:",
        "Answer": "religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 223,
        "Question": "The Constitution provides that the 'separation of church and state shall be inviolable.' This is implemented most by the constitutional principles embodied in:",
        "Answer": "the non-establishment clause."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 224,
        "Question": "b. Distinguish fully between the 'free exercise of religion clause' and the 'non-establishment of religion clause'. ",
        "Answer": "B. The freedom of exercise of religion entails the right to believe, which is absolute, and the right to act on one's belief, which is subject to regulation. As a rule, the freedom of exercise of religion can be restricted only if there is a clear and present danger of a substantive evil which the state has the right to prevent. The non establishment clause implements the principle of seperation of church and state. The state cannot set up a church. Pass laws that aid one religion, and all religions, prefer one religion over another force or influence a person to go to or remain away from church against his will, of force him to profess a belief or disbelief in any religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 225,
        "Question": "The Gangnam Style’s Witnesses (whose tenets are derogatory to the Catholic Church), applied for a permit to use the public plaza and kiosk to hold their religious meeting on the occasion of their founding anniversary. Mayor Lebron allowed them to use the north-western part of the plaza but not the kiosk (which is a few meters away from the Catholic church). Members of the Gangnam Style Witnesses claim that the act of Mayor Lebron is a violation of their freedom of assembly and religion. Is this correct?",
        "Answer": "No, because historical experience shows that peace and order may be disturbed whenever two opposing religious groups or beliefs expound their dogmas."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 226,
        "Question": "Alimighty Apostles is a relatively new religious group and movement with fast-growing membership. One time, DeepThroat, an investigative reporter, made a research and study as to what the group’s leader, Maskeraid was actually doing. DeepThroat eventually came up with the conclusion that Maskeraid was a phony who is just fooling the simpleminded people to part with their money in exchange for the promise of eternal happiness in some far-away heaven. This was published in a newspaper which caused much agitation among the followers of Maskeraid. Some threatened violence against DeepThroat, while some others already started destroying properties while hurting those selling the newspaper. The local authorities, afraid of the public disorder that such followers might do, decided to ban the distribution of the newspaper containing the article. DeepThroat went to court complaining about the prohibition placed on the dissemination of his article. He claims that the act of the authorities partakes of the nature of heckler’s veto, thus a violation of the guaranty of press freedom. On the other hand, the authorities counter that the act was necessary to protect the public order and the greater interest of the community. If you were the judge, how would you resolve the issue? ",
        "Answer": "If I were the judge, I would rule that the distribution of the newspaper cannot be banned. Freedom of the news should be allowed although it induces a condition of unrest and stirs people to anger. Freedom of the press includes freedom of circulation. When governmental action that restricts freedom of the press is based on content, it is given the strictest scrutiny and the government must shoe that there is a clear and present danger of the substantive evil which the government has the right to prevent. The threats of violence and even the destruction of properties while hurting those selling the newspaper do not constitute a clear and present danger as to warrant curtailment of the right of Deep Throat to distribute the newspaper."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 227,
        "Question": "Candida has been administratively charged of immorality for openly living with Manuel, a married man. Candida urges that her conjugal arrangement with Manuel fully conforms with their religious beliefs and with the teachings of their church. In resolving whether Candida should be administratively penalized which is the best test to apply? ",
        "Answer": "Compelling State Interest Test."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 228,
        "Question": "To fulfill a campaign promise to the poor folk in a far-flung area in Mindanao, the President requested his friend, Pastor Roy, to devote his ministry to them. The President would pay Pastor Roy a monthly stipend of P50,00000 from his discretionary fund, and would also erect a modest house of worship in the locality in an area of the latter's choice. Does the President thereby violate any provisions of the Constitution? Explain your answer.",
        "Answer": "Yes, the President violates the non-establishment clause. The use of public funds to erect a house of worship and to pay a religious leader constitutes excessive government entanglement with religion and favors one religion over others, violating the principle of separation of church and state."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 229,
        "Question": "A law is passed requiring all public school teachers to attend a weekly values formation seminar conducted by a specific religious group. A teacher who is a member of a different religion challenges the law. Is the law constitutional? Explain.",
        "Answer": "No, the law is unconstitutional. It violates the non-establishment clause by favoring one specific religious group and compelling attendance at its seminars, thus excessively entangling the government with religion and infringing on the religious freedom of teachers belonging to other faiths."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 230,
        "Question": "The City of Manila passed an ordinance banning the sale of all religious literature in public places without a permit. A religious group challenges the ordinance. What constitutional test should the court apply? Explain.",
        "Answer": "The court should apply the strict scrutiny test. The ordinance regulates religious literature, which touches upon both freedom of speech and the free exercise of religion. The government must show a compelling state interest and that the ordinance is narrowly tailored to achieve that interest."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 231,
        "Question": "A public school allows its facilities to be used by various religious groups for their worship services after school hours, charging a standard fee for maintenance. A taxpayer sues, claiming this violates the Constitution. Decide.",
        "Answer": "The practice is constitutional. Allowing temporary, non-preferential use of public facilities by various religious groups, with a standard fee, does not constitute an establishment of religion. It is a neutral accommodation that serves a secular purpose of community use and does not favor any specific religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 232,
        "Question": "A government agency provides financial assistance for medical services to all indigent patients, including those in religiously affiliated hospitals. A citizen challenges this, arguing it amounts to state funding of religion. Is the challenge valid?",
        "Answer": "No, the challenge is not valid. The financial assistance is provided directly to indigent patients for the secular purpose of healthcare, regardless of the hospital's religious affiliation. This is a neutral, generally available benefit that does not constitute state funding of religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 233,
        "Question": "A law grants a tax exemption only to religious organizations that have been in existence for at least 50 years. A newly formed religious group challenges the law. What is the likely outcome?",
        "Answer": "The law is likely unconstitutional. It creates a classification among religious organizations based on the duration of their existence, which is not a substantial distinction related to a compelling state interest. It violates the equal protection clause and the non-establishment clause by favoring older religions."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 234,
        "Question": "May a public school teacher be prohibited from wearing a religious headscarf (hijab) in the classroom? Explain.",
        "Answer": "Generally, no. Prohibiting a teacher from wearing a hijab likely violates her free exercise of religion. The government must show a compelling state interest, such as a specific, concrete harm to the educational process, and that the prohibition is the least restrictive means to achieve that interest. Mere speculation about disruption is insufficient."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 235,
        "Question": "A local government unit donates a parcel of public land to a church for the construction of a new cathedral. Is this donation valid?",
        "Answer": "No, the donation is invalid. The direct donation of public land to a religious institution for the construction of a place of worship constitutes an establishment of religion, violating the non-establishment clause. It provides an exclusive benefit to one religion using public resources."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 236,
        "Question": "A state university includes a course on 'Comparative Religion' in its general education curriculum. A student claims this violates the non-establishment clause. Decide.",
        "Answer": "The course does not violate the non-establishment clause. It has a secular purpose of providing academic knowledge about various religions, does not promote or inhibit religion, and avoids excessive government entanglement with religion. It is a permissible study of religion, not religious indoctrination."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 237,
        "Question": "A law provides that only Filipino citizens may be members of the clergy in religious organizations operating in the Philippines. Is this law constitutional?",
        "Answer": "The law is likely unconstitutional. It infringes on the internal governance of religious organizations and the free exercise of religion by dictating the qualifications for clergy based on citizenship, which is not a compelling state interest in the context of religious ministry."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 238,
        "Question": "May the government require religious organizations to disclose their sources of funding and expenditures?",
        "Answer": "Yes, but only if the requirement is neutral, generally applicable, and serves a compelling state interest, such as preventing fraud or financial crimes. The disclosure must be the least restrictive means to achieve that interest and not unduly burden the free exercise of religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 239,
        "Question": "A religious group holds a procession on a public highway without a permit, causing significant traffic disruption. The local government disperses the procession. Was the dispersal valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the dispersal was valid. The government has a compelling interest in ensuring public order and safety and regulating the use of public thoroughfares. The requirement of a permit for such activities is a content-neutral regulation of the time, place, and manner of assembly, applied without discrimination."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 240,
        "Question": "A public school official leads a prayer during a graduation ceremony. Is this permissible?",
        "Answer": "No, it is not permissible. A prayer led by a school official at a public school graduation constitutes state-sponsored religious activity, violating the non-establishment clause. It places the state's imprimatur on a particular religious practice and coerces attendance and participation."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 241,
        "Question": "A law exempts religious publications from the value-added tax (VAT). Is this exemption constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the exemption is likely constitutional. Tax exemptions for religious, charitable, and educational entities are traditionally permitted and do not necessarily violate the establishment clause, especially if they are part of a broader pattern of exemptions for non-profit organizations and do not involve excessive entanglement."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 242,
        "Question": "May a judge display the Ten Commandments in his courtroom?",
        "Answer": "It depends on the context. If the display is part of a broader historical or educational exhibit showing various legal traditions, it might be permissible. However, if it is a solitary display with a predominantly religious purpose, it likely violates the non-establishment clause by endorsing a particular religious tradition."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 243,
        "Question": "A government agency provides funding for a social welfare program run by a religious organization, but the funds are strictly used for secular services like feeding programs and medical clinics. Is this funding valid?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the funding is valid. The government may provide financial assistance to religious organizations for the delivery of secular social services, provided the funds are not used for religious worship, instruction, or proselytization, and the selection of recipients is based on neutral, secular criteria."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 244,
        "Question": "A public school allows student-led prayer groups to meet on school premises before classes begin. Is this allowed?",
        "Answer": "Yes, this is generally allowed under the Equal Access Act principle. If the school creates a limited open forum for student activities, it cannot discriminate against student groups based on the religious content of their speech. The meetings must be student-initiated and student-led."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 245,
        "Question": "A city ordinance bans all door-to-door solicitation, including by religious groups seeking to proselytize. A religious group challenges the ordinance. What is the result?",
        "Answer": "The ordinance is likely unconstitutional as applied to religious proselytizing. While the government has an interest in protecting residential privacy, a complete ban on door-to-door religious solicitation is not narrowly tailored and substantially burdens the free exercise of religion and freedom of speech."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 246,
        "Question": "May a religious organization be compelled to hire a minister of a different faith?",
        "Answer": "No. The 'ministerial exception' derived from the Free Exercise Clause prohibits the government from interfering with a religious organization's choice of who will perform spiritual functions. Compelling the hiring of a minister of a different faith would violate the core of religious autonomy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 247,
        "Question": "A law grants a religious organization an exclusive franchise to operate all cemeteries in a province. Is this law valid?",
        "Answer": "No, the law is invalid. Granting an exclusive franchise to one religious organization for a public utility like cemeteries violates the non-establishment clause by giving a governmental monopoly to a specific religion and excessively entangles the state with religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 248,
        "Question": "A public university denies official recognition to a student religious group that requires its leaders to adhere to its religious tenets. The university argues this violates its non-discrimination policy. Is the university's action correct?",
        "Answer": "No, the university's action is incorrect. Forcing a religious student group to accept leaders who do not share its beliefs would violate the group's freedom of expressive association and free exercise of religion. The university's non-discrimination policy, as applied in this context, is not a compelling enough interest to justify this intrusion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 249,
        "Question": "A government program provides vouchers to parents to send their children to private schools, including religious schools. Is this program constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, such a program can be constitutional. If the program is neutral with respect to religion and provides aid directly to parents based on private, independent choices, it does not violate the establishment clause. The government aid reaches religious schools only as a result of genuine and independent private choice."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 250,
        "Question": "A religious group seeks a permit to use a public park for a large religious festival. The local government denies the permit, citing potential noise and traffic, but grants permits to other large non-religious events. What is the legal issue?",
        "Answer": "The denial likely violates the Free Exercise and Free Speech clauses. The government cannot discriminate against religious speech in a public forum. The reasons given (noise, traffic) must be applied neutrally to all similar events, regardless of their content. The denial appears to be based on the religious content of the event, which is unconstitutional."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 251,
        "Question": "May a public school require students to recite the pledge of allegiance, which includes the phrase 'under God'?",
        "Answer": "Compelling students to recite the pledge, including the phrase 'under God,' likely violates the Free Exercise rights of students whose religious beliefs conflict with this phrase. While the pledge itself, as a patriotic ceremony, may be generally permissible, forcing participation in a religiously laden statement is problematic. Students must have the right to opt out."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 252,
        "Question": "A zoning law prohibits the construction of new buildings over 50 feet tall in a residential area. A church plans to build a steeple that is 60 feet tall and is denied a variance. The church sues. What is the likely outcome?",
        "Answer": "The church has a strong claim under the Religious Land Use and Institutionalized Persons Act (RLUIPA) or its constitutional equivalents. If the zoning law imposes a substantial burden on the church's religious exercise (e.g., building a steeple for religious reasons) and the government cannot show a compelling interest achieved by the least restrictive means, the church should prevail."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 253,
        "Question": "A state law mandates a moment of 'silent meditation' in all public schools at the start of each day. Is this law constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the law is likely constitutional. A moment of silent meditation is neutral in purpose and effect. It does not promote religion over non-religion and provides a period for silent reflection that can be used for secular or religious purposes based on the individual student's choice, avoiding coercion and state endorsement of religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 254,
        "Question": "A government employee is fired for posting religious verses on his private social media account criticizing his government agency. Can he be legally fired?",
        "Answer": "He likely cannot be fired solely for the religious content of his private speech. As a public employee, his speech on matters of public concern (like criticism of his agency) is protected by the First Amendment. The government must show that its interests in promoting the efficiency of public services outweigh the employee's free speech and free exercise rights, which is a high bar for private social media posts."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 255,
        "Question": "A law provides that religious organizations are immune from suit for any torts committed by their employees. Is this law valid?",
        "Answer": "No, the law is likely invalid. Granting religious organizations blanket immunity from tort liability, where other organizations are not immune, violates the Establishment Clause by providing a special benefit to religion. It also potentially denies victims their right to access courts and seek redress, raising due process concerns."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 256,
        "Question": "A religious university that receives some state funding expels a student for violating its moral code based on religious doctrine. The student sues. Can the university be compelled to reinstate the student?",
        "Answer": "Generally, no. Courts grant significant deference to the decisions of religious educational institutions on matters of discipline related to their religious tenets. Compelling reinstatement would involve the court in interpreting religious doctrine, violating the Free Exercise Clause and the principle of church autonomy."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 257,
        "Question": "A city council opens its sessions with a prayer offered by a rotating group of clergy from different faiths. A citizen challenges this practice. Is the practice constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the practice is constitutional under the precedent set in *Town of Greece v. Galloway*. Legislative prayer is a historical tradition that does not violate the Establishment Clause, so long as the practice does not coerce participation and does not denigrate or proselytize non-adherents. A rotating roster of clergy from different faiths supports its neutrality."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 258,
        "Question": "A public hospital has a chaplaincy program funded by the government to provide spiritual comfort to patients. Is this program permissible?",
        "Answer": "The program may be permissible if it is administered neutrally. The government has a legitimate secular interest in addressing the holistic needs of patients, including spiritual care. However, the program must not favor one religion, must accommodate the requests of patients of all faiths or no faith, and must avoid coercing patients, to avoid violating the Establishment Clause."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 259,
        "Question": "A law prohibits all forms of religious proselytizing within 500 meters of any place of worship of another religion. A religious group challenges the law. What is the constitutional issue?",
        "Answer": "The law likely violates the Free Exercise and Free Speech clauses. It is a content-based restriction on religious speech that is not narrowly tailored to serve a compelling state interest. While the government may have an interest in preventing religious disturbances, a blanket ban on proselytizing within a large radius is overly broad and suppresses core religious expression."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 260,
        "Question": "A public school district adopts a policy allowing student religious clubs to use school facilities for meetings during non-instructional time, on the same basis as other non-curricular student groups. A parent sues, claiming this violates the Establishment Clause. Is the policy constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the policy is constitutional under the Equal Access Act and relevant jurisprudence. If a public school creates a limited open forum for student-led non-curricular groups, it cannot discriminate against groups based on the religious content of their speech. The meetings must be student-initiated and student-led, and school officials may not be involved in the religious activities."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 261,
        "Question": "A state law requires all public officials, including judges, to swear an oath ending with the phrase 'so help me God.' An atheist public official refuses to take the oath and is barred from office. Is this constitutional?",
        "Answer": "No, this is likely unconstitutional. Requiring a public official to swear an oath including 'so help me God' violates the Establishment Clause by effectively imposing a religious test for public office. The government must provide a secular alternative oath that does not compel affirmation of a belief in God."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 262,
        "Question": "A municipal ordinance prohibits the distribution of any written materials on public sidewalks without prior approval from the city mayor. A religious group challenges the ordinance after being denied permission to distribute religious pamphlets. What is the likely outcome?",
        "Answer": "The ordinance is likely unconstitutional. It constitutes a prior restraint on speech, particularly religious speech, and grants unbridled discretion to the mayor. Content-based restrictions on speech in a traditional public forum like sidewalks must be narrowly tailored to serve a compelling state interest, which this ordinance fails to do."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 263,
        "Question": "A law grants tax exemptions only to religious organizations that have been in operation for more than 25 years. A newly established religious group is denied the exemption and challenges the law. What constitutional principle is violated?",
        "Answer": "The law violates the Equal Protection Clause and likely the Establishment Clause. Creating a distinction based solely on the age of a religious organization is not substantially related to an important government interest and constitutes an arbitrary classification that favors established religions over newer ones."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 264,
        "Question": "A public university receives a donation to establish a scholarship fund exclusively for students belonging to a particular religious denomination. Can the university accept and administer this scholarship?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the university can generally accept and administer such a scholarship if the selection criteria are based on the donor's private choice and the university's administration is neutral. However, the university must ensure it does not appear to be endorsing the religion and that other scholarship opportunities remain available to all students regardless of religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 265,
        "Question": "A city council passes an ordinance banning all outdoor religious services in residential areas between 10 PM and 6 AM, citing noise concerns. A church that holds midnight services challenges the ordinance. What is the constitutional test applied?",
        "Answer": "The court will apply the Sherbert/Yoder compelling state interest test. The ordinance substantially burdens the free exercise of religion. The government must show a compelling state interest in noise control and that the ordinance is the least restrictive means to achieve that interest. A total ban may not be the least restrictive means if limited noise regulations could suffice."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 266,
        "Question": "A public school teacher wears a large crucifix necklace while teaching. The school district orders her to remove it, citing a policy against visible religious symbols. Does this violate her constitutional rights?",
        "Answer": "Yes, this likely violates her Free Exercise rights. The government must show a compelling state interest for restricting religious expression, and merely having a policy against visible religious symbols without evidence of actual disruption to the educational process is insufficient. The teacher's private religious expression is protected unless it amounts to government endorsement of religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 267,
        "Question": "A state law provides funding to religious schools for the purchase of secular textbooks. Is this constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, this is constitutional under the 'child benefit' theory. The aid benefits students rather than the religious institution, is provided for secular purposes, and is neutral toward religion. The textbooks must be the same as those used in public schools and cannot be used for religious instruction."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 268,
        "Question": "A religious organization operates a restaurant that is open to the public but refuses to serve customers who do not adhere to its religious beliefs. The customers file a discrimination suit. What is the likely outcome?",
        "Answer": "The religious organization would likely lose the case. While religious freedom is protected, a business open to the public generally must comply with anti-discrimination laws. The government has a compelling interest in preventing discrimination in public accommodations, which outweighs the religious objection in this context."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 269,
        "Question": "A city ordinance requires all religious organizations to obtain a special permit to conduct any form of charitable fundraising. Secular charities are exempt from this requirement. A religious group challenges the ordinance. What constitutional violation exists?",
        "Answer": "The ordinance violates the Equal Protection Clause and the Free Exercise Clause. It creates a content-based distinction that discriminates against religious speech and activity. The government must show a compelling interest for treating religious charities differently from secular ones, which would be difficult to establish here."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 270,
        "Question": "A public school allows its facilities to be used for after-school programs by various community groups but refuses access to a religious group that wants to hold Bible study classes. The religious group sues. What is the legal principle?",
        "Answer": "This violates the Free Speech clause under the 'limited public forum' doctrine. Once a government entity opens its facilities for public use, it cannot discriminate against speech based on its religious content. The religious group must be given equal access to the facilities under the same terms as other community groups."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 271,
        "Question": "A state law exempts religious organizations from complying with building safety codes for their places of worship. A building inspector attempts to enforce the codes against a church. What constitutional defense is available to the church?",
        "Answer": "The church could raise a Free Exercise defense, arguing that compliance with the building codes substantially burdens its religious exercise. However, the government would likely prevail as building safety codes serve a compelling government interest in public safety and are generally applicable laws that are neutral toward religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 272,
        "Question": "A public university denies recognition to a student religious organization that requires its leaders to be of the same faith. The university claims this violates its non-discrimination policy. What is the constitutional issue?",
        "Answer": "This violates the religious group's freedom of expressive association and free exercise rights. Forcing a religious student organization to accept leaders who do not share its beliefs would fundamentally interfere with the group's ability to express its religious message and maintain its religious character."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 273,
        "Question": "A municipal government displays a nativity scene alone on the front lawn of city hall during the Christmas season. A citizen sues, claiming this violates the Establishment Clause. What is the likely outcome?",
        "Answer": "The display likely violates the Establishment Clause. A solitary nativity scene on government property constitutes an endorsement of Christianity. To be constitutional, religious displays must be part of a larger exhibit that includes secular holiday symbols, creating a context that shows the government is recognizing the holiday season rather than endorsing a particular religion."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 274,
        "Question": "A religious school receives government funding for a school lunch program. The school requires all students to participate in daily religious services. Can the government condition its funding on the school ending this requirement?",
        "Answer": "Yes, the government can impose such conditions. While religious schools have free exercise rights, when they accept government funds, the government may require that the funds not be used to support religious activities. This condition serves the compelling interest in preventing government funding of religion and is narrowly tailored to that purpose."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 275,
        "Question": "A state legislature opens each session with a prayer delivered by a state-employed chaplain who is always of the same denomination. A legislator from a different faith tradition objects. What constitutional problem exists?",
        "Answer": "This practice likely violates the Establishment Clause. While legislative prayer is generally permissible, the consistent selection of chaplains from only one denomination shows a preference for a particular religion. The selection process should be non-discriminatory and inclusive of different faith traditions to avoid the appearance of denominational preference."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 276,
        "Question": "A religious organization owns a for-profit business that provides commercial services to the public. The business refuses to provide services for same-sex weddings based on religious objections. What constitutional protections apply?",
        "Answer": "The business is unlikely to succeed with a Free Exercise claim. While religious beliefs are protected, when operating a for-profit business open to the public, the business must generally comply with neutral, generally applicable anti-discrimination laws. The government's compelling interest in preventing discrimination outweighs the religious objection in this commercial context."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 277,
        "Question": "A public school district implements a moment of silence at the beginning of each school day. The statute authorizing this states its purpose is to allow students to 'pray, meditate, or reflect.' Is this constitutional?",
        "Answer": "Yes, this is likely constitutional. A moment of silence is neutral in purpose and effect, serving both secular and religious purposes. It does not coerce students to pray and allows for individual choice. The inclusion of the word 'pray' does not invalidate the statute if the primary purpose is secular and it accommodates all students equally."
    },
    {
        "subject": "Political Law",
        "No": 278,
        "Question": "A city denies a zoning permit to a church that wants to build in a commercial zone, while approving similar permits for secular assemblies like theaters and meeting halls. What constitutional claim does the church have?",
        "Answer": "The church has a strong claim under the Religious Land Use and Institutionalized Persons Act (RLUIPA) and the Free Exercise Clause. This constitutes unequal treatment and a substantial burden on religious exercise. The city must show a compelling government interest and that its zoning decision is the least restrictive means of achieving that interest."
    }
];